<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap.maintenance">
 <title>Maintaining Appliance Images</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KIWI</primary>
 <secondary>maintenance</secondary></indexterm>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   Whenever you create an appliance as described in <xref
   linkend="chap.appliance"/>, you are using a snapshot of the software
   repositories. As time goes by, the software continues to develop and the
   image becomes outdated. Something similar applies to the appliance
   configuration, which may become outdated when, for example, the network
   setup has changed or services have been replaced. Last, it may be necessary
   to update the image description itself, for example to add or change
   repositories. To prevent an image from becoming outdated, KIWI provides
   means to <emphasis>maintain</emphasis> existing images.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term><command>kiwi --upgrade</command></term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <option>--upgrade</option> option can be used to update a previously
     built image without making any changes to the image description. It
     requires an existing unpacked root tree. This option can be used to update
     software packages within an image. Since it only modifies an existing
     root tree, it is faster than re-building an image from scratch.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>kiwi --prepare</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In case the appliance configuration or the image description needs to be
     changed, the image root tree needs to be rebuilt with
     <option>--prepare</option> in order to make these changes permanent. We
     using this method to upgrade an existing image, it is recommended to put
     the image description under a version control system such as git or
     subversion. This allows to track the changes and to easily switch between
     image versions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>

 <sect1 id="sec.maintenance.packages">
  <title>Image Maintenance: Updating Software Packages</title>
  <para>
   The quickest way to produce an updated image containing the latest software
   versions from the repositories configured in the image description is to
   use KIWI's <option>--upgrade</option> option. It optionally allows to
   specify additional repositories (such as an update repository) or packages
   on the command line. Using <option>--upgrade</option> requires an existing
   unpacked image tree from a previous run of <command>kiwi
   --prepare</command>.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure you know the path to the existing unpacked root tree. In the
     following we assume it is located at <filename
     class="directory">/tmp/myISO</filename>. If you need to add additional
     repositories, note down the paths and types.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the following command to update the unpacked root tree from the
     repositories configured in the image description:
    </para>
    <screen>kiwi --upgrade /tmp/myISO</screen>
    <para>
     You can optionally specify additional repositories not yet configured in
     the image description, or additional packages and/or patterns. The latter
     two can be part of the added repositories or the ones already configured.
    </para>
    <screen>kiwi --upgrade /tmp/myISO --add-repo <replaceable>REPO</replaceable> --add-repotype <replaceable>REPO_TYPE</replaceable> \
--add-package <replaceable>PACKAGE</replaceable> --add-pattern <replaceable>pattern</replaceable></screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run <command>kiwi --create</command> to build the final image. The
     following example assumes that the image is created in
     <filename>/tmp</filename>:
    </para>
    <screen>kiwi --create /tmp/myISO --destdir /tmp</screen>
   </step>   
  </procedure>

  <warning>
   <title>Adding Repositories, Packages or Patterns</title>
   <para>
    Repositories, packages or patterns that you specify with the --add-*
    commands are not added to the image description! Therefore these additions
    are not permanent and need to be specified again with the next run. If you
    want to make these additions permanent, proceed as described in <xref
    linkend="sec.maintenance.config"/>.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <important>
   <title>Configuration Changes</title>
   <para>
    Running KIWI with the <option>--upgrade</option> option does not rebuild
    the root tree&mdash;it only manipulates the existing version that was
    created with the last <option>--prepare</option>-run. Changes to the image
    description that have been made after the last
    <option>--prepare</option>-run, have no effect when running the
    <option>--upgrade</option> option.
   </para>
   <para>
    In case of un-applied configuration changes, rebuild the unpacked root
    tree from scratch with <command>kiwi --prepare</command>.
   </para>
  </important>
  
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.maintenance.config">
  <title>Image Maintenance: Modifying the Configuration</title>
  <para> 
   In case you need to change the configuration of the appliance (see <xref
   linkend="sec.appliance.kiwi-model"/>) or the image description (see <xref
   linkend="chap.description"/> you need to rebuild the complete image tree by
   running <command>kiwi --prepare</command>, to make your changes
   permanent. It is strongly recommended to put your image description under a
   version control system to enable tracking of changes and different version
   builds.
  </para> 
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Put your image description directory under a version control system such
     as git. This step is optional, but strongly recommended.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change the image description as needed. Stick to the following general
     rules: 
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       To add packages or patterns, modify the respective entries in
       <filename>configuration.xml</filename>. See <xref
       linkend="sec.description.packages"/> for details.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To change the list of repositories, modify the respective entries in
       <filename>configuration.xml</filename>. See <xref
       linkend="sec.description.repository"/> for details.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To change the configuration of your appliance, modify the respective
       files in the overlay tree or provide an updated archive.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To change the user-defined tasks that will be carried out after the
       installation (for example activating services), adjust the
       <filename>configuration.sh</filename> script.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create an unpacked root tree by running <command>kiwi
     --prepare</command>. The following example assumes that the image
     description is located under
     <filename>/tmp/myISO_config</filename> and that the result is
     written to <filename>/tmp/myISO</filename>:
    </para>
    <screen>kiwi --prepare /tmp/myISO_config --root /tmp/myISO</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run <command>kiwi --create</command> to build the final image. The
     following example assumes that the image is created in
     <filename>/tmp</filename>:
    </para>
    <screen>kiwi --create /tmp/myISO --destdir /tmp</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Once the final version of your changes has been applied, make sure to
     check this state in to the version control system. 
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  
  <important>
   <title>Do not Manipulate the Unpacked Root Image</title>
   <para>
    The unpacked image directory is just a directory, as far as the build
    system is concerned and you can manipulate the content of this directory
    according to your needs. Since it represents a system installation you can
    “chroot” into this directory for testing purposes. The file system
    contains an additional directory named /image that is not present in a
    regular system. It contains information KIWI requires during the create
    step, including a copy of the config.xml file.
   </para>
   <para>
    Do not make any changes to the system, since they will get lost when
    re-running the prepare step again. Whatsmore, you may introduce errors
    that will occur during the create step, that are difficult to track. The
    recommended way to apply changes to the unpacked image directory is to
    change the configuration and re-run the prepare step as described above.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
