<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap.installation">
 <title>Installation</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KIWI</primary>
 <secondary>Installation</secondary></indexterm>
 <sect1 id="sec.installation.rpminstall">
  <title>Installing KIWI Packages</title>

  <para>
   KIWI is shipped with all SUSE distributions, but not installed by
   default. With SUSE Linux Enterprise 11, KIWI is included in the 
   software development kit (SDK), not the main installation media.
   A minimum KIWI installation requires installing the 
   <package>kiwi</package> packag eand at least one package containing
   the boot descriptions for the various image types:
  </para>
  <simplelist>
   <member>
    <package>kiwi-desc-isoboot</package>: Live ISO boot templates
   </member>
   <member>
    <package>kiwi-desc-netboot</package>: PXE network boot templates
   </member>
   <member>
    <package>kiwi-desc-oemboot</package>: Expandable Virtual Machine boot
    templates
   </member>
   <member>
    <package>kiwi-desc-vmxboot</package>: Virtual Machine boot templates
   </member>
  </simplelist>
  <para>
   It is also recommended to install the package <package>kiwi-doc</package>
   containing the documentation. For a complete list of KIWI packages run the
   command <command>zypper se kiwi</command>.
  </para>
  
  <sect2 id="sec.installation.rpminstall.latest">
   <title>Installing the Latest Version Available</title>
   <para>
    KIWI is an active project and new releases are published
    regularly. Packages with the latest KIWI version for all SUSE
    distributions that are actively maintained can be obtained from the
    Virtualization:Appliances repository at <ulink
    url="http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Virtualization:/Appliances/"/>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.installation.fromsource">
  <title>Running KIWI from a Source Checkout</title>

  <para>
   KIWI is developed and maintained in a repository on GitHub. You can
   clone the source code using the following command.
  </para>

  <screen>git clone https://github.com/openSUSE/kiwi.git</screen>

  <para>
   Before running KIWI make sure all its dependencies are fullfilled. Get a list
   of required packages by running the following command in the checkout
   directory (<filename class="directory">kiwi/</filename>):
  </para>
  
  <screen>awk '/BuildRequires:/ { print $2 | "sort" }' rpm/kiwi.spec</screen>

  <para>
   Once all dependent packages are installed run the test suite from the
   checkout directory as follows
  </para>

  <screen><command>make</command> test</screen>

  <para>
   If all tests pass, all dependencies are fullfilled and KIWI can be run with
   from the checkout directory with the following command:
  </para>

  <screen><command>./kiwi</command></screen>

  <para>
   To update to the latest version available, run <command>git pull</command>
   from the KIWI checkout directory.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
