<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap.migration">
 <title>System Analysis/Migration</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KIWI</primary>
 <secondary>image analysis</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  KIWI provides a module which allows you to analyze the running system for
  creating a report and an image description representing the current state of
  the machine. Among others, this allows you to clone your currently running
  system into an image. The process has the following limitations at the
  moment:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Works for SUSE systems only (with zypper on board)
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The process works semi-automatically&mdash;depending on the
    complexity of the system, some manual postprocessing might be necessary
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  When calling KIWI's analysis module it tries to find the base version of
  your operating system by using the active repositories specified in the
  zypper database to identify the software packages currently installed. The
  result is a list of packages and patterns representing your system. Files
  not belonging to any packages, such as user data or configuration files, are
  provided as custom data by KIWI. In addition, KIWI offers different data
  visualization e.g unmanaged binary data. Along with the software analysis,
  KIWI also checks for enabled systemd services, augeas configuration
  inventory and more. The process will not go beyond the scope of local
  file systems.
 </para>
 <para>
  To create an image of your running system, proceed as follows:
 </para>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Create a report listing all packages and repositories currently installed
    by running
   </para>
   <screen>sudo kiwi --describe workstation</screen>
   <para>
    The result will be written to /var/cache/kiwi/describe/workstation
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Check the result of the previous step for packages that cannot be assigned
    to a repository. If you do not need these packages within your image,
    proceed with the next step. If you want them to be in the image, either
    add the repositories containing these packages to your system (for
    example with <command>zypper addrepo</command>) and run the previous
    command again. Alternatively, tell KIWI which additional repos to check,
    by using the previous command together with the
    <option>--add-repo</option> and <option>--add-repotype</option> options
    (refer to <command>man 1 kiwi</command> for more information).
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Rerun the report generating command. List all packages that are not part
    of a repository or should not be included with the <option>--skip</option>
    parameter. In case you have previously used the
    <option>--add-repo</option> and <option>--add-repotype</option> options,
    use them again with this command:

    <remark condition="clarity">
     2015-12-22 - fs: --skip and --nofiles are not mentioned in "man 1 kiwi"
    </remark>

   </para>

   <screen><command>kiwi</command> --describe workstation --nofiles \
--skip "<replaceable>LIST_OF_PAKAGES</replaceable>" \
--add-repo <replaceable>REPO</replaceable> --add-repotype <replaceable>TYPE</replaceable></screen>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Next check the list of files not belonging to any packages in
    <filename>/var/cache/kiwi/describe/workstation/custom.files</filename>. Among
    others, this list contains user data, configuration files, and database
    files. Make sure to only add files to the image that are really needed. In
    case you want to publish the image, double check the list for password
    files, configuration files containing plain text passwords, user data,
    databases and other sensitive data. All files that should become part of
    the image description need to be moved from <filename
    class="directory">/var/cache/kiwi/describe/worksation/custom</filename> to
    <filename>/var/cache/kiwi/describe/worksation/root</filename>. For
    additional information also check <filename>/var/cache/kiwi/describe/workstation/custom.files.readme</filename>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Adjust the image description according to your needs by checking the
    following items:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change author and contact in <filename>config.xml</filename>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Set appropriate name for your image in <filename>config.xml</filename>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Add or modify the image type (<literal>oem</literal> by default) set in
      <filename>config.xml</filename> if needed.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you want to access any remote file system its a good idea to let
      AutoYaST add them on first boot of the system.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Check the network setup in
      <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network</filename>. Is this setup still
      possible in the cloned environment? Make sure you check for the MAC
      address of the card first.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Check the size of the image description. It's good practice to keep the
    image as small as possible. The size of a migrated image description
    mainly depends on how many overlay files exists in the <filename
    class="directory">root/</filename> directory. You should make sure to
    maintain only required overlay files.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Create an image from the description. By default an OEM image, containing
    a virtual disk that can also be deployed to a physical machine, is
    created. In addition to that, an ISO image containing an installable
    version of the image, is also generated. Refer to <xref
    linkend="chap.oem"/> for details.
   </para>
<screen><command>kiwi</command> --build /var/cache/kiwi/describe/workstation -d /tmp/myResult</screen>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Test the image as described in <xref linkend="sec.oem.testing"/>.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</chapter>
