<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>Introduction</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <sect1 id="sec.introduction.whatiskiwi">
    <title>What is KIWI?</title>
      <para>KIWI is an image build system for Linux.</para>
      <para>A Linux image may present itself in many different formats,
    for example the <filename class="extension">*.iso</filename> file you
    download to burn a distribution installation file to optical media is an
    image. A file used by virtualization systems such as KVM, Xen, or VMware
    is an image. The installation of a Linux system on your hard drive can be
    turned into an image using the <command>dd</command> command.</para>
    <para>Basically, you can think of an image as a Linux system in a file.
    Depending on the type of the image you are dealing with you have different
    options for using the image. For example you can burn an ISO image to
    optical media and then boot your computer from the CD/DVD, or you can run
    a Virtual Machine from the <filename class="extension">*.iso</filename>
    file (image) stored on your hard drive.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sec.introduction.whatdoeskiwido">
    <title>What does KIWI do?</title>
      <para>KIWI builds images in a variety of formats.</para>
      <para>As an image build tool, KIWI builds images in a relatively large
    number of supported image formats. The details of the image creation
    process are explained in the <xref linkend="chap.workflow"/> chapter. The
    image format of the image produced by KIWI is defined within a
    configuration file named <filename>config.xml</filename>
    or <filename>*.kiwi</filename> as described in
    <xref linkend="chap.description"/>.</para>
      <para>Note that not all elements and attributes that may be used in
    the KIWI <filename>config.xml</filename> configuration file are listed
    or described in this document. The complete schema documentation
    can be accessed on the web at
    <ulink url="http://doc.opensuse.org/projects/kiwi/schema-doc/"/>, latest
    version, or on your local system using the <filename>
    file:///usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/schema/kiwi.html</filename> path
    as the URL in the browser.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sec.introduction.howtousekiwi">
    <title>How do I use KIWI?</title>
      <para>KIWI is a command line tool that is invoked with the
    <command>kiwi</command> command in your shell. KIWI needs to be executed
    as the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user, as administrative privileges are
    required for many operations that need to take place to create an image.
    Therefore, when using KIWI you need to be aware of what you are doing and
    a certain amount of caution is in order. Running KIWI on your system is
    not inherently dangerous to your system, just keep in mind that you are
    running as the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user.</para>
      <para>An image is created in a two step process as described in the
    <xref linkend="chap.workflow"/> chapter. Use
    <command>kiwi --prepare</command> for the first step and
    <command>kiwi --create</command> for the second step. For user convenience
    KIWI also has the <option>--build</option> that combines the
    <emphasis>prepare</emphasis> and <emphasis>create</emphasis> steps.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
