<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chap.introduction">
 <title>Introduction</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KIWI</primary>
 <secondary>Introduction</secondary></indexterm>
 <sect1 id="sec.introduction.whatiskiwi">
  <title>What is KIWI?</title>

  <para>
   KIWI is an image build system for Linux.
  </para>

  <para>
   Images for Linux are available in many different formats. A Linux <filename
   class="extension">*.iso</filename> file, that can be burned to an optical
   medium to install Linux, is an image. A file used by virtualization systems
   such as KVM, Xen, or VMware is an image. The installation of a Linux system
   on your hard drive can be turned into an image using the
   <command>dd</command> command.
  </para>
  <para>
   Basically, an image is a Linux system in a file. Depending on the type of
   the image, there are different use cases for it. It can be used to burn an
   iso image to an optical medium with which the computer can be booted. An
   image can also be used to run a Virtual Machine from the
   <filename class="extension">*.iso</filename> file (image) stored on your
   hard drive.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.introduction.whatdoeskiwido">
  <title>What does KIWI do?</title>
  <para>
   KIWI allows you to configure, build, and deploy your own operating system
   images in a variety of formats. The KIWI workflow is divided into two
   distinct stages. For a detailed description of this process refer to <xref
   linkend="chap.workflow"/>.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Preparation</title>
     <para>
      Create a root directory holding the contents of the new file
      system. Install the required packages from a software package source
      such as SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. Create an image description file,
      (<filename>config.xml</filename>) and optionally apply
      customizations. This operation results in the <quote>unpacked root
      tree</quote>.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
   <step>
    <formalpara>
     <title>Creation</title>
     <para>
      The image itself is created using the unpacked root tree created in the
      prvious step. The image creation process does not require user
      interaction, but can be fine-tuned by modifying the images.sh script
      that is called during the creation process.
     </para>
    </formalpara>
   </step>
  </procedure>  
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 id="sec.introduction.howtousekiwi">
  <title>How to use KIWI?</title>

  <para>
   KIWI is a command line tool that is invoked with the
   <command>kiwi</command> command in your shell. KIWI needs to be executed
   as the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user, as
   administrative privileges are required for many operations that need to
   take place to create an image. Therefore, when using KIWI you need to be
   aware of what you are doing and a certain amount of caution is in order.
   Running KIWI on your system is not inherently dangerous to your system,
   just keep in mind that you are running as the
   <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user.
  </para>

  <para>
   The two phases of the image creation process outlined in <xref
   linkend="sec.introduction.whatdoeskiwido"/> can be started with the
   commands <command>kiwi --prepare</command> for the first step and
   <command>kiwi --create</command> for the second step. For convenience KIWI
   also has the <option>--build</option> that combines the
   <emphasis>prepare</emphasis> and <emphasis>create</emphasis> steps.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
