<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.description">
  <title>KIWI Image Description</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>image description</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>In order to be able to create an image with KIWI, a so called
    image description must be created. The image description is
    represented by a directory which has to contain at least one file
    named <filename>config.xml</filename> or <filename
      class="extension">*.kiwi</filename>. A good start for such a
    description can be found in the examples provided in
      <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/examples</filename>. </para>

  <figure id="fig.description.imagedescrdir">
    <title>Image Description Directory</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="description.svg" width="40%" format="SVG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="description.png" width="40%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The following additional information is optional for the process
    of building an image, but most often mandatory for the functionality
    of the created operating system: </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>images.sh</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para> Optional configuration script while creating the packed
          image. This script is called at the beginning of the image
          creation process. It is designed to clean-up the image system.
          Affected are all the programs and files only needed while the
          unpacked image exists. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>config.sh</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Optional configuration script while creating the unpacked
          image. This script is called at the end of the installation,
          but <emphasis>before</emphasis> the package scripts have run.
          It is designed to configure the image system, such as the
          activation or deactivation of certain services (<systemitem
            class="service">insserv</systemitem>). The call is not made
          until after the switch to the image has been made with chroot.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename class="directory">root</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Subdirectory that contains special files, directories, and
          scripts for adapting the image environment
            <emphasis>after</emphasis> the installation of all the image
          packages. The entire directory is copied into the root of the
          image tree using <command>cp</command>
          <option>-a</option>. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>config-yast-autoyast.xml</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para> Configuration file which has been created by AutoYaST. To
          be able to create such an AutoYaST profile, run: </para>
        <screen><command>yast2</command> autoyast</screen>
        <para>Once you have saved the information from the AutoYaST UI
          as <filename>config-yast-autoyast.xml</filename> file in your
          image description directory KIWI will process on the file and
          setup your image as follows: </para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>While booting the image YaST is started in AutoYaST
              mode automatically </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The AutoYaST description is parsed and the
              instructions are handled by YaST. In other words the
                <emphasis>system configuration</emphasis> is performed
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If the process finished successfully the environment
              is cleaned and AutoYaST won’t be called at next reboot.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>config-cdroot.tgz</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para> Archive which is used for ISO images only. The data in
          the archive is uncompressed and stored in the CD/DVD root
          directory. This archive can be used, for example, to integrate
          a license file or information directly readable from the CD or
          DVD. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename>config-cdroot.sh</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Along with the <filename>config-cdroot.tgz</filename> one
          can provide a script which allows to manipulate the extracted
          data. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename class="directory">config/</filename></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>Optional subdirectory that contains Bash scripts that are
          called after the installation of all the image packages,
          primarily in order to remove the parts of a package that are
          not needed for the operating system. The name of the Bash
          script must resemble the package name listed in the
          config.xml. </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <sect1 id="sec.description.config.xml">
    <title>The config.xml File</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>KIWI</primary>
      <secondary>config.xml</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para> The mandatory image definition file is divided into different
      sections which describes information like the image name and type
      as well as the packages and patterns the image should consist of. </para>
    <para>The following information explains the basic structure of the
      XML document. When KIWI is executed, the XML structure is
      validated by the KIWI RELAX&nbsp;NG based schema. For details on
      attributes and values please refer to the schema documentation
      file at
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/kiwi.rng.html</filename>. </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.image">
      <title><sgmltag>image</sgmltag> Element</title>
      <screen>&lt;image schemaversion="6.2" name="iname"
  displayname="text" 
  kiwirevision="number" 
  id="10 digit number"&gt;
  <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> ... </sgmltag>
&lt;/image&gt;</screen>

      <para>The image definition starts with an <sgmltag>image</sgmltag>
        tag and requires the schema format at version 2.0. The attribute
          <sgmltag class="attribute">name</sgmltag> specifies the name
        of the image which is also used for the filenames created by
        KIWI. Because we don’t want spaces in filenames the <sgmltag
          class="attribute">name</sgmltag> attribute must not have any
        spaces in its name. </para>
      <para>The following optional attributes can be inserted in the
          <sgmltag>image</sgmltag> tag: </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">displayname</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Allows setup of the boot menu title for the selected
              bootloader. So you can have <emphasis>suse-SLED-foo</emphasis>
              as the image name but a different name as the boot display name.
              Spaces are not allowed in the display name because it causes
              problems for some bootloaders and kiwi did not take the effort
              to separate the ones which can display them correctly from the
              ones which can't</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">kiwirevision</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>specifies a KIWI git revision number which is known to
              build a working image from this description. If the KIWI
              git revision doesn't match the specified value, the process
              will exit. The currently used git revision can be queried
              by calling <command>kiwi</command>
              <option>--version</option>. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para> sets an identification number which appears as file
                <filename>/etc/ImageID</filename> within the image.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Inside the <sgmltag>image</sgmltag> section the following
        mandatory and optional subelements exists. The simplest image
        description must define the elements
          <sgmltag>description</sgmltag>,
        <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag>, <sgmltag>repository</sgmltag>
        and <sgmltag>packages</sgmltag> (at least one of <sgmltag
          class="attribute">type</sgmltag>="<sgmltag class="attvalue"
          >bootstrap</sgmltag>"). </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.description">
      <title><sgmltag>description</sgmltag> Element</title>
      <screen>&lt;description type="system"&gt;
  &lt;author&gt;an author&lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;contact&gt;mail&lt;/contact&gt;
  &lt;specification&gt;short info&lt;/specification&gt;
&lt;/description&gt;</screen>

      <para>The mandatory <sgmltag>description</sgmltag> section
        contains information about the creator of this image
        description. The attribute <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >type</sgmltag> could be either of the value system which
        indicates this is a system image description or at value boot
        for boot image descriptions. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.profiles">
      <title><sgmltag>profiles</sgmltag> Element</title>
      <screen>&lt;profiles&gt;
   &lt;profile name="name" description="text"/&gt;
   <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> ... </sgmltag>
&lt;/profiles&gt;</screen>

      <para>The optional <sgmltag>profiles</sgmltag> section lets you
        maintain one image description while allowing for variation of
        the sections packages and drivers that are included. A separate
        profile element must be specified for each variation. The
          <sgmltag>profile</sgmltag> child element, which has <sgmltag
          class="attribute">name</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
          class="attribute">description</sgmltag> attributes, specifies
        an alias name used to mark sections as belonging to a profile,
        and a short description explaining what this profile does. </para>

      <para>To mark a set of packages/drivers as belonging to a profile,
        simply annotate them with the <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >profiles</sgmltag> attribute. It is also possible to mark
        sections as belonging to multiple profiles by separating the
        names in the <sgmltag class="attribute">profiles</sgmltag>
        attribute with a comma. If a <sgmltag>packages</sgmltag> or
          <sgmltag>drivers</sgmltag> tag does not have a <sgmltag
          class="attribute">profiles</sgmltag> attribute, it is assumed
        to be present for all profiles. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.preferences">
      <title><sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag> Element</title>

      <screen>&lt;preferences profiles="name"&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.1.2&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;packagemanager&gt;zypper&lt;/packagemanager&gt;
  &lt;type image="name" ...&gt;
    &lt;machine|oemconfig|pxedeploy|size|split|systemdisk|vagrantconfig&gt;
  &lt;/type&gt; 
&lt;/preferences&gt;</screen>

      <para>The mandatory <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag> section
        contains information about the supported image type(s), the used
        package manager, the version of this image, and optional
        attributes. The image version must be a three-part version
        number of the format: <emphasis role="bold"
          >Major</emphasis>.<emphasis role="bold"
          >Minor</emphasis>.<emphasis role="bold">Release</emphasis>.
        <indexterm>
          <primary>KIWI</primary>
          <secondary>release format</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        In case of changes to the image description the following rules
        should apply: </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>For smaller image modifications that do not add or
            remove any new packages, only the release number is
            incremented. The <filename>config.xml</filename> file
            remains unchanged. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>For image changes that involve the addition or removal
            of packages the minor number is incremented and the release
            number is reset. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>For image changes that change the size of the image file
            the major number is incremented. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>By default, KIWI uses the <command>zypper</command> package
        manager but it is also possible to use the non SUSE native package
        manager called <command>smart</command>. </para>

      <para>In general the specification of one
          <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag> section is sufficient. However,
        it’s possible to specify multiple <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag>
        sections and distinguish between the sections via the <sgmltag
          class="attribute">profiles</sgmltag> attribute. Data may also
        be shared between different profiles. Using profiles it is
        possible to, for example, configure specific preferences for OEM
        image generation. Activation of a given
          <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag> during image generation is
        triggered by the use of the <option>--add-profile</option>
        command line argument.</para>


      <para>For each <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag> block at least one
          <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> element must be defined. It is
        possible to specify multiple <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> elements in
        any <sgmltag>preferences</sgmltag> block. To set a given
          <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> description as the default image use
        the boolean attribute <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >primary</sgmltag> and set its value to <sgmltag
          class="attvalue">true</sgmltag>. The image type to be created
        is determined by the value of the <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >image</sgmltag> attribute. The following list describes the
        supported types and possible values of the image attribute: </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">lxc|docker</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the lxc or docker image type to build a linux container image
              For additional information refer to the <xref linkend="chap.lxc"/>
              chapter.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">[filesystem]</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use one of the following image types to build a plain
              filesystem image. This will create a file containing the
              data in the specified filesystem and you can loop mount
              the image to view the contents e.g image="ext3":</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem>
          <para>ext2</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
          <para>ext3</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
          <para>ext4</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
          <para>btrfs</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
          <para>squashfs</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem>
          <para>xfs</para>
                 </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">tbz</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the tbz image type to just pack the unpacked image tree
              into a tarball.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">cpio</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the cpio image type to specify the generation of a
              boot image (initrd). When generating a boot image, it is
              possible to specify a specific boot profile and boot
              kernel using the optional <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >bootprofile</sgmltag>="<sgmltag class="attvalue"
                >default</sgmltag>" and <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >bootkernel</sgmltag>="<sgmltag class="attvalue"
                >std</sgmltag>" attributes. </para>
            <para>A boot image should group the various supported
              kernels into profiles. If the user chooses not to use the
              profiles supplied by KIWI, it is required that one profile
              named std be created. This profile will be used if no
              other bootkernel is specified. Further it is required to
              create a profile named default. This profile is used when
              no bootprofile is specified. </para>
            <para>It is recommended that special configurations that
              omit drivers, use special drivers and/or special packages
              be specified as profiles. </para>
            <para>The bootprofile and bootkernel attribute are respected
              within the definition of a system image. Us the attribute
              and value <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >type</sgmltag>="<sgmltag class="attvalue"
                >system</sgmltag>" of the <sgmltag>description</sgmltag>
              element to specify the creation of a system image. The
              values of the bootprofile and bootkernel attributes are
              used by KIWI when generating the boot image. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">iso</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specify the key-value pair <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag class="attvalue"
                >iso</sgmltag>" to generate a live system suitable for
              deployment on optical media (CD or DVD). Use the <sgmltag
                class="attribute">boot</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
                class="attvalue">isoboot/suse-*</sgmltag>" attribute
              when generating this image type to select the appropriate
              boot image for optical media. In addition the optional
                <sgmltag class="attribute">flags</sgmltag> attribute may
              be set to the following values with the effects described
              below:</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">seed</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Creates a btrfs based compressed read-only
                    filesystem which allows write operations into a btrfs
                    seed device. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">overlay</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Creates a squashfs based compressed read-only
                    filesystem which is combined with a write space via
                    the overlayfs filesystem. overlayfs is part of the
                    kernel since version 3.7</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attvalue"
                  >compressed</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Creates a split ext3 plus squashfs filesystem and
                    combines them via a symlink system to a complete system
                    it is recommended to specify a <sgmltag>split</sgmltag>
                    section as a child of this type element.     
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>If the flags attribute is not used the filesystem
              will be squashfs compressed for /bin /boot /lib /lib64 /opt /sbin
              and /usr. The rest of the filesystem is packed into a tmpfs
              and linked via symbolic links 
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">oem</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use this type to create a virtual disk system suitable
              in a preload setting. In addition specify the attributes
                <sgmltag class="attribute">filesystem</sgmltag>, and
                <sgmltag class="attribute">boot</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
                class="attvalue">oemboot/suse-*</sgmltag>" to control
              the filesystem used for the virtual and to specify the
              proper boot image. Using the optional <sgmltag
                class="attribute">format</sgmltag> attribute and
              setting, the value to iso or usb will create self
              installing images suitable for optical media or a USB
              stick, respectively. Booting from the media will deploy
              the OEM preload image onto the selected storage device of
              the system. It is also possible to configure the system to
              use logical volumes. Use the optional <sgmltag
                class="attribute">lvm</sgmltag> attribute and specify
              the logical volume configuration with the
                <sgmltag>systemdisk</sgmltag> child element. The default
              volume group name is kiwiVG. Further configuration of the
              image is performed using the appropriate
                <sgmltag>*config</sgmltag> child block. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">pxe</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Creating a network boot image is supported by KIWI
              with the image="pxe" type. When specifying the creation of
              a network boot image use the <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >filesystem</sgmltag> and boot="netboot/suse-*"
              attributes to specify the filesystem of the image and the
              proper boot image. To compress the image file set the
                <sgmltag class="attribute">compressed</sgmltag> boolean
              attribute to true. This setting will compress the image
              file and has no influence on the filesystem used within
              the image. The compression is often use to support better
              transfer times when the pxe image is pushed to the boot
              server over a network connection. The pxe image layout is
              controlled by using the <sgmltag>pxedeploy</sgmltag> child
              element. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">split</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The split image support allows the creation of an
              image as split files. Using this technique one can assign
              different filesystems and different read-write properties
              to the different sections of the image. The
                <sgmltag>oem</sgmltag>, <sgmltag>pxe</sgmltag>,
                <sgmltag>usb</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag>vmx</sgmltag> types
              can be created as a split system image. Use the <sgmltag
                class="attribute">boot</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
                class="attvalue">oem|netboot|usb|vmx/suse-*</sgmltag>"
              attribute to select the underlying type of the split
              image. The attributes <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >fsreadwrite</sgmltag>, <sgmltag class="attribute"
                >fsreadonly</sgmltag> are used to control the
              read-write properties of the filesystem specified as the
              attributes value. Use the appropriate
                <sgmltag>*config</sgmltag> child block to specify the
              properties of the underlying image. For example when
              building a OEM based split image use the
                <sgmltag>oemconfig</sgmltag> child section. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">vmx</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Creation of a virtual disk system is enabled with the
              vmx value of the image attribute. Set the filesystem of
              the virtual disk with the filesystem attribute and select
              the appropriate boot image by setting <sgmltag
                class="attribute">boot</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
                class="attvalue">vmxboot/suse-*</sgmltag>" The optional
              format attribute is used to specify one of the
              virtualization formats supported by QEMU, such as vmdk
              (also the VMware format) or qcow2. For the virtual disk
              image the optional vga attribute may be used to configure
              the kernel framebuffer device. Acceptable values can be
              found in the Linux kernel documentation for the
              framebuffer device (see
                <filename>Documentation/fb/vesafb.txt</filename>). KIWI
              also supports the selection of the bootloader for the
              virtual disk according to the rules indicated for the USB
              system. Last but not least the virtual disk system may
              also be created with a LVM based layout by using the
                <sgmltag class="attribute">lvm</sgmltag> attribute. The
              previously indicated rules apply. Use the
                <sgmltag>machine</sgmltag> child element to specify
              appropriate configuration of the virtual disk system.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Within the type section, there could be other optional
    attributes which are either universally valid or can be used
    for different image types in the same way. The following list
        explains these attributes: </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
          >kernelcmdline</sgmltag></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Specifies additional kernel parameters.
          The following example disables kernel messages:
          <literal>kernelcmdline="quiet"</literal></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
        <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
                    >mdraid</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>For disk based image types, aka oem and vmx,
          mdraid activates the creation of a software raid image.
          The raid inside the image is created in degraded mode
          because at creation time we only know about one disk.
          It's in the hand of the user to add devices to the raid
          after the image runs on the target machine. The value
          for mdraid can be either <emphasis>mirroring</emphasis>
          or <emphasis>striping</emphasis>, which means the raid
          level is set to RAID1 (mirroring) or
          RAID0 (striping).</para>
                </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

      <para>Within the preferences section, there are the following
        optional elements: </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
              >showlicense</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
               Specifies the base name of a license file which is displayed in oem
               images before the installation happens. It's possible to add more showlicense
               sections to display more licenses one after the other. If no such element
               is specified the default 'license' and 'EULA' files are searched. The
               search algorithm will append the .txt or .locale.txt suffix to the license
               name to form the license file name. You should make sure that you license
               files contains this suffix.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
              >rpm-check-signatures</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies whether RPM should check the package
              signature or not </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
            >rpm-excludedocs</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para> Specifies whether RPM should skip installing package
              documentation </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">rpm-force</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies whether RPM should be called with
                <option>--force</option>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">keytable</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the name of the console keymap to use. The
              value corresponds to a map file in
                <filename>/usr/share/kbd/keymaps</filename>. The
                <varname>KEYTABLE</varname> variable in
                <filename>/etc/sysconfig/keyboard</filename> file is set
              according to the keyboard mapping. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">timezone</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the time zone. Available time zones are
              located in the <filename class="directory"
                >/usr/share/zoneinfo</filename> directory. Specify the
              attribute value relative to <filename class="directory"
                >/usr/share/zoneinfo</filename>. For example, specify
              Europe/Berlin for
                <filename>/usr/share/zoneinfo/Europe/Berlin</filename>.
              KIWI uses this value to configure the timezone in
                <filename>/etc/localtime</filename> for the image. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">locale</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para> Specifies the name of the UTF-8 locale to use, which
              defines the contents of the <envar>RC_LANG</envar> system
              environment variable in
                <filename>/etc/sysconfig/language</filename>. Please
              note only UTF-8 locales are supported here which also
              means that the encoding must <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
              part of the locale information. The KIWI schema validates
              the locale string according to the following
                pattern:<literal>[a-z]{2}_[A-Z]{2}(,[a-z]{2}_[A-Z]{2})*</literal>.
              This means you have to specify the locale like the
              following example: en_US or en_US,de_DE </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">bootsplash-theme</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the name of the bootsplash theme to use </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">bootloader-theme</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the name of the gfxboot theme to use </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
            >defaultdestination</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Used if the <option>--destdir</option> option is not
              specified when calling KIWI</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">defaultroot</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Used if the option <option>--root</option> is not
              specified when calling KIWI </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>

      <para>The <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> element may contain child
        elements to provide specific configuration information for the
        given type. The following lists the supported child elements: </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag>systemdisk</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using the optional systemdisk section it is possible to
              create a LVM (Logical Volume Management) based storage
              layout. By default, the volume group is named
              <emphasis>kiwiVG</emphasis>. It
              is possible to change the name of the group by setting the
              <sgmltag class="attribute">name</sgmltag> attribute
              to the desired name. Individual volumes within the volume
              group are specified using the
              <sgmltag class="element">volume</sgmltag> element. </para>
            <para>The following example shows the creation of a volume
              named <emphasis role="italic">usr</emphasis> and a volume
              named <emphasis role="italic">var</emphasis> inside the volume
              group systemVG.</para>
            <screen> &lt;systemdisk name="systemVG"&gt; 
  &lt;volume name="usr" freespace="100M"/&gt; 
  &lt;volume name="var" size="200M"/&gt; 
&lt;/systemdisk&gt;</screen>
            <para>The optional attribute
              <sgmltag class="attribute">freespace</sgmltag> controls the
              amount of unused space available after software has been
              installed in the given volume. By default the available space
              of a created volume is between 10% and 20%. Using the optional
              <sgmltag class="attribute">size</sgmltag> attribute the
              absolute size of the given volume is specified. The
              <sgmltag class="attribute">size</sgmltag> attribute takes
              precedence over the
              <sgmltag class="attribute">freespace</sgmltag> attribute. If
              the specified size is insufficient, based on the estimated
              software install size for the given volume, the specified
              value will be ignored and a volume with default settings will
              be created. This implies that the volume will be 80% to 90%
              full. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag>oemconfig</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>By default, the oemboot process will create or modify
              a swap, and <filename>/</filename> partition. It is possible to
              influence the behavior by the <filename>oem-*</filename>
              elements explained below.</para>
            <screen>&lt;oemconfig&gt;
   &lt;oem-systemsize&gt;2000&lt;/oem-systemsize&gt;
   &lt;oem-... &gt; 
&lt;/oemconfig&gt;</screen>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-boot-title</sgmltag>text<sgmltag class="endtag"
                    >oem-boot-title</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>By default, the string <phrase remap="verb"
                      >OEM</phrase> will be used as the boot manager
                    menu entry when KIWI creates the GRUB configuration
                    during deployment. The
                      <sgmltag>oem-boot-title</sgmltag> element allows
                    you to set a custom name for the grub menu entry.
                    This value is represented by the
                      <varname>kiwi_oemtitle</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-bootwait</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-bootwait</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the system should wait for user interaction
                    priot to  continuing the boot process after the oem image
                    has been dumped to the designated storage device (default
                    value is false). This value is represented by the
                    <varname>kiwi_oembootwait</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-inplace-recovery</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-inplace-recovery</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the recovery archive is stored as part of
                    the image or if the archive is to be created at the time
                    the image is deployed to the target storage device.
                    <varname>kiwi_oemrecoveryInPlace</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-kiwi-initrd</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-kiwi-initrd</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>If this element is set to true (default value is
                    false) the oemboot boot image (initrd) will
                      <emphasis>not</emphasis> be replaced by the system
                    (mkinitrd) created initrd. This option is useful
                    when the system is installed on removable storage
                    such as a USB stick or a portable external drive.
                    For movable devices it is potentially necessary to
                    detect the storage location during every boot. This
                    detection process is part of the oemboot boot image.
                    This value is represented by the
                    <varname>kiwi_oemkboot</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-partition-install</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-partition-install</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the image is to be installed into a
                      free partition on the target storage device. By default
                      the value is false and Kiwi installs images to a
                      target device which causes data loss on the device. With
                      <sgmltag class="element">oem-partition-install</sgmltag>
                      set to true any other settings that have influence on
                      the partition table, such as
                      <sgmltag class="element">oem-swap</sgmltag> are ignored.
                      This value is represented by the
                      <varname>kiwi_oempartition_install</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-reboot</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-reboot</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the system is to be rebooted after
                    the oem image has been deployed to the designated
                    storage device (default value is false). This value
                    is represented by the <varname>kiwi_oemreboot</varname>
                    variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-reboot-interactive</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-reboot-interactive</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the system is to be rebooted after
                    the oem image has been deployed to the designated
                    storage device (default value is false). Prior to
                    reboot a message is posted and must be acknowledged
                    by the user in order for the system to reboot. This value
                    is represented by the
                    <varname>kiwi_oemrebootinteractive</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-recovery</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-recovery</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>If this element is set to true (default value is
                    false), KIWI will create a recovery archive from the
                    prepared root tree. The archive will appear as
                      <filename>/recovery.tar.bz2</filename> in the
                    image file. During first boot of the image a single
                    recovery partition will be created and the recovery
                    archive will be moved to the recovery partition. An
                    additional boot menu entry is created that when
                    selected restores the original root tree on the
                    system. The user information on the <filename
                      class="directory">/home</filename> partition or in
                    the <filename class="directory">/home</filename>
                    directory is not affected by the recovery process.
                    This value is represented by the kiwi_oemrecovery
                    variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-recoveryID</sgmltag>partition-id<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-recoveryID</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify the partition type for the recovery
                    partition. The default is to create a Linux
                    partition (id = 83). This value is represented by
                    the <varname>kiwi_oemrecoveryID</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-silent-boot</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-silent-boot</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the system should boot in silent mode
                    after the oem image has been deployed to the designated
                    storage device (default value is false). This value
                    is represented by the <varname>kiwi_oemsilentboot</varname>
                    variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-shutdown</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-shutdown</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the system is to be powered down after
                    the oem image has been deployed to the designated
                    storage device (default value is false). This value
                    is represented by the <varname>kiwi_oemshutdown</varname>
                    variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-shutdown-interactive</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-shutdown-interactive</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if the system is to be powered down after
                    the oem image has been deployed to the designated
                    storage device (default value is false). Prior to
                    shutdown a message is posted and must be acknowledged
                    by the user in order for the system to power off. This
                    value is represented by the
                    <varname>kiwi_oemshutdowninteractive</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                    >oem-swap</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag class="endtag"
                    >oem-swap</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify if a swap partition should be created.
                    The creation of a swap partition is the default
                    behavior. This value is represented by the
                      <varname>kiwi_oemswap</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                  >oem-swapsize</sgmltag>number in MB<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-swapsize</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Set the size of the swap partition. If a swap
                    partition is to be created and the size of the swap
                    partition is not specified with this optional
                    element, KIWI will calculate the size of the swap
                    partition and create a swap partition equal to two
                    times the RAM installed on the system at initial
                    boot time. This value is represented by the
                      <varname>kiwi_oemswapMB</varname> variable in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                  >oem-systemsize</sgmltag>number in MB<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-systemsize</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Set the size the operating system is allowed to
          consume on the target disk. The size limit does not
          include any consideration for swap space or a
          recovery partition.
          In a setup <emphasis>without</emphasis> a
          <sgmltag class="element">systemdisk</sgmltag> element
          this value specifies the size of the root partition.
          In a setup <emphasis>including</emphasis>
          a <sgmltag class="element">systemdisk</sgmltag> element
          this value specifies the size of the LVM partition which
          contains all specified volumes. Thus, the sum of all
          specified volume sizes plus the sum of the specified
          freespace for each volume must be smaller or equal
          to the size specified with the
          <sgmltag class="element">oem-systemsize</sgmltag>.
          This value is represented by the variable
          <varname>kiwi_oemrootMB</varname> in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="starttag"
                  >oem-unattended</sgmltag>true|false<sgmltag
                    class="endtag">oem-unattended</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The installation of the image to the target system
                      occurs automatically without requiering user
                      interaction. If multiple possible target devices are
                      discovered the image is deployed to the first device.
                      <varname>kiwi_oemunattended</varname> in the initrd</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag>pxedeploy</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Information contained in the optional
                <sgmltag>pxedeploy</sgmltag> section is only considered
              if the <sgmltag class="attribute">image</sgmltag>
              attribute of the <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> element is set to
                <sgmltag class="attvalue">pxe</sgmltag>. In order to use
              a PXE image it is necessary to create a network boot
              infrastructure. Creation of the network boot
              infrastructure is simplified by the KIWI provided package
                <package>kiwi-pxeboot</package>. This package configures
              the basic PXE boot environment as expected by KIWI pxe
              images. The <package>kiwi-pxeboot</package> package
              creates a directory structure in
                <filename>/srv/tftpboot</filename>. Files created by the
              KIWI create step need to be copied to the
                <filename>/srv/tftpboot</filename> directory structure.
              For additional details about the PXE image please refer
              to the PXE Image chapter later in this document. </para>

            <para>In addition to the image files it is necessary that
              information be provided about the client setup. This
              information, such as the image to be used or the
              partitioning, is contained in a file with the name
                  <filename>config.<replaceable>MAC</replaceable></filename>
              in the directory <filename>/srv/tftpboot/KIWI</filename>.
              The content of this file is created automatically by KIWI
              if the pxedeploy section is provided in the image
              description. A pxedeploy section is outlined below: </para>
            <screen>&lt;pxedeploy server="IP" blocksize="4096"&gt;
   &lt;timeout&gt;seconds&lt;/timeout&gt;
   &lt;kernel&gt;kernel-file&lt;/kernel&gt;
   &lt;initrd&gt;initrd-file&lt;/initrd&gt; 
   &lt;partitions device="/dev/sda"&gt; 
     &lt;partition type="swap" number="1" size="MB"/&gt; 
     &lt;partition type="L" number="2" size="MB"
              mountpoint="/" target="true"/&gt; 
     &lt;partition type="fd"  number="3"/&gt; 
   &lt;/partitions&gt; 
   &lt;union ro="dev" rw="dev" type="clicfs"/&gt; 
   &lt;configuration source="/KIWI/../file" dest="/../file" arch="..."/&gt;
   &lt;configuration .../&gt; 
&lt;/pxedeploy&gt; </screen>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <sgmltag class="attribute">server</sgmltag>
                  attribute is used to specify the IP address of the PXE
                  server. The <sgmltag class="attribute"
                    >blocksize</sgmltag> attributes specifies the
                  blocksize for the image download. Other protocols are
                  supported by KIWI but require the
                    <parameter>kiwiserver</parameter> and
                    <parameter>kiwiservertype</parameter> kernel
                  parameters to be set when the client boots. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The value of the optional
                    <sgmltag>timeout</sgmltag> element specifies the
                  grub timeout in seconds to be used when the KIWI
                  initrd configures and installs the grub boot loader on
                  the client machine after the first deployment to allow
                  standalone boot. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Passing kernel parameters is possible with the use
                  of the optional <sgmltag class="attribute"
                    >kernelcmdline</sgmltag> attribute in the
                    <sgmltag>type</sgmltag> section. The value of this
                  attribute is a string specifying the settings to be
                  passed to the kernel by the GRUB bootloader. The KIWI
                  initrd includes these kernel options when installing
                  grub for standalone boot </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The optional <sgmltag>kernel</sgmltag> and
                    <sgmltag>initrd</sgmltag> elements are used to
                  specify the file names for the kernel and initrd on
                  the boot server respectively. When using a special
                  boot method not supported by the distribution’s
                  standard mkinitrd, it is imperative that the KIWI
                  initrd remains on the PXE server and also be used for
                  local boot. If the configured image uses the
                    <sgmltag>split</sgmltag> type or the
                    <sgmltag>pxedeploy</sgmltag> section includes any
                  union information the kernel and initrd elements must
                  be used. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <sgmltag>partitions</sgmltag> section is
                  required if the system image is to be installed on a
                  disk or other permanent storage device. Each partition
                  is specified with one partition child element. The
                  mandatory type attribute specifies the partition type
                  id.</para>
                  <para>The required <sgmltag class="attribute"
                    >number</sgmltag> attribute provides the number
                  of the partition to be created. The size of the
                  partition may be specified with the optional size
                  attribute. The optional mountpoint attribute provides
                  the value for the mount point of the partition. The
                  optional boolean target attribute identifies the
                  partition as the system image target partition. KIWI
                  always generates the swap partition as the first
                  partition of the netboot boot image. By default, the
                  second partition is used for the system image. Use the
                  boolean <sgmltag class="attribute">target</sgmltag>
                  attribute to change this behavior. Providing the value
                  image for the <sgmltag class="attribute"
                    >size</sgmltag> attribute triggers KIWI into
                  calculating the required size for this partition. The
                  calculated size is sufficient for the created image.
                  </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>If the system image is based on a read-only
                  filesystem such as squashfs and should be mounted in
                  read-write mode use the optional union element. The
                  type attribute is used to specify one of the supported
                  overlay filesystem <systemitem class="filesystem">clicfs</systemitem>
                  Use the ro
                  attribute to point to the read only device and the rw
                  attribute to point to the read-write device. </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>The optional <sgmltag>configuration</sgmltag>
                  element is used to integrate a network client’s
                  configuration files that are stored on the server. The
                  source attribute specifies the path on the server for
                  the file to be downloaded. The dest attribute
                  specifies destination of the downloaded file on the
                  network client starting at the root (/) of the
                  filesystem. Multiple configuration elements may be
                  specified such that multiple files can be transferred
                  to the network client. In addition configuration files
                  can be bound to a specific client architecture by
                  setting the optional arch attribute. To specify
                  multiple architectures use a comma separated string.
                </para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag>size</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use the size element to specify the image size in
              Megabytes or Gigabytes. The unit attribute specifies
              whether the given value will be interpreted as Megabytes
                (<sgmltag class="attribute">unit</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
                class="attvalue">M</sgmltag>") or Gigabytes (<sgmltag
                class="attribute">unit</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
                class="attvalue">G</sgmltag>"). The optional boolean
              attribute additive specifies whether or not the given size
              should be added to the size of the generated image or not. </para>
            <para>In the event of a size specification that is too small
              for the generated image, KIWI will expand the size
              automatically unless the image size exceeds the specified
              size by 100 MB or more. In this case KIWI will generate an
              error and exit. </para>
            <para>Should the given size exceed the necessary size for
              the image KIWI will not alter the image size as the free
              space might be required for proper execution of components
              within the image. </para>
            <para>If the size element is not used, KIWI will create an
              image containing approximately 30 % free space. </para>
            <screen>&lt;size unit="M"&gt;1000&lt;/size&gt;</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag>split</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>For images of type split or iso the information
              provided in the optional <sgmltag>split</sgmltag> section
              is considered if the compressed attribute is set to
              true. With the configuration in this block it is possible
              to determine which files are writable and whether these
              files should be persistently writable or temporarily. Note
              that for ISO images only temporary write access is
              possible. </para>
            <para>When processing the provided configuration KIWI
              distinguishes between directories and files. For example,
              providing <filename class="directory">/etc</filename> as
              the value of the name attribute indicates that the
                <filename class="directory">/etc</filename> directory
              should be writable. However, this does not include any of
              the files or sub-directories within <filename
                class="directory">/etc</filename>. The content of /etc
              is populated as symbolic links to the read-only files. The
              advantage of setting only a directory to read-write access
              is that any newly created files will be stored on the disk
              instead of in <systemitem class="filesystem"
                >tmpfs</systemitem>. Creating read-write access to a
              directory and it’s files requires two specifications as
              shown below. </para>
            <screen>&lt;split&gt; 
  &lt;temporary&gt; 
    <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> read/write access to </sgmltag>
    &lt;file name="/var"/&gt; 
    &lt;file name="/var/*"/&gt; 
    <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> but not on this file: </sgmltag>
    &lt;except name="/etc/shadow"/&gt; 
  &lt;/temporary&gt;
  &lt;persistent&gt;
    <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> persistent read/write access to: </sgmltag>
    &lt;file name="/etc"/&gt; 
    &lt;file name="/etc/*"/&gt; 
    <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> but not on this file: </sgmltag>
    &lt;except name="/etc/passwd"/&gt; 
  &lt;/persistent&gt;
&lt;/split&gt;</screen>
            <para>Use the except element to specify exceptions to
              previously configured rules. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag>machine</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The optional machine section serves to specify
              information about a VM guest machine. Using the data
              provided in this section, KIWI will create a guest
              configuration file required to run the image on the target
              machine. </para>
            <para>If the target is a VMware virtual machine indicated by
              the format attribute set to vmdk, KIWI creates a VMware
              configuration file. If the target is a Xen virtual machine
              indicated by the domain attribute in the machine section
              KIWI will create a Xen guest config file. </para>
            <para>The sample block below shows the general outline of
              the information that can be specified to generate the
              configuration file </para>
            <screen>&lt;machine arch="arch" memory="MB"
  HWversion="number" guestOS="suse|sles"
  domain="dom0|domU"/&gt; 
   &lt;vmconfig-entry&gt;Entry_for_VM_config_file&lt;\vmconfig-entry&gt;
   &lt;vmconfig-entry .../&gt;
   &lt;vmnic driver="name" interface="number" mode="mode"/&gt; 
   &lt;vmnic ...&gt;
   &lt;vmdisk controller="ide|scsi" id="number"/&gt; 
   &lt;vmdvd  controller="ide|scsi" id="number"/&gt; 
&lt;/machine&gt; </screen>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">arch</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The virtualized architecture. Supported values
                    are <sgmltag class="attvalue">ix86</sgmltag> or
                      <sgmltag class="attvalue">x86_64</sgmltag>. The
                    default value is <sgmltag class="attvalue"
                      >ix86</sgmltag>. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">memory</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The mandatory <sgmltag class="attribute"
                      >memory</sgmltag> attribute specifies how much
                    memory in MB should be allocated for the virtual
                    machine </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
                  >HWversion</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The VMware hardware version number, the default
                    value is <sgmltag class="attvalue">3</sgmltag>.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
                  >guestOS</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The guest OS identifier. For the ix86
                    architecture the default value is suse and for the
                    x86_64 architecture suse-64 is the default. At this
                    point only the SUSE and SLES guestOS types are
                    supported. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">domain</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The Xen domain setup. This could be either a
                    dom0 which is the host machine hosting the guests
                    and therefore doesn’t require a configuration file,
                    or it could be set to domU which indicates this is a
                    guest and also requires a guest configuration which
                    is created by KIWI. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Use the <sgmltag class="element">vmconfig-entry</sgmltag>
              element to create entries in the virtual machine's configuration
              file; .vmx for VMware images and .xenconfig for Xen images.
              You may specify as many configuration options as desired. The
              value of the <sgmltag class="element">vmconfig-entry</sgmltag>
              element is expected to be specified in the syntax required by
              the VM configuration file to be written. The value is free
              format text and is not validated by Kiwi in any way. The entry
              is written to the VM configuration file verbatime.</para>
            <para>Use the <sgmltag class="element">vmdisk</sgmltag> element
              to setup the virtual main storage device.</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
                  >controller</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> Supported values for the mandatory <sgmltag
                      class="attribute">controller</sgmltag> attribute
                    are <sgmltag class="attvalue">ide</sgmltag> and
                      <sgmltag class="attvalue">scsi</sgmltag>. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The mandatory <sgmltag class="attribute"
                      >id</sgmltag> attribute specifies the disk id. If
                    only one disk is set the id value should be set to
                    0. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">device</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The device attribute specifies the disk that
                    should appear in the para virtual instance.
                    Therefore only relevant for Xen </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Use the <sgmltag class="element">vmdvd</sgmltag> element
              to setup a virtual optical drive (CD/DVD) connection</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
                  >controller</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> Supported values for the mandatory <sgmltag
                      class="attribute">controller</sgmltag> attribute
                    are <sgmltag class="attvalue">ide</sgmltag> and
                      <sgmltag class="attvalue">scsi</sgmltag>. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The mandatory <sgmltag class="attribute"
                      >id</sgmltag> attribute specifies the disk id. If
                    only one disk is set the id value should be set to
                    0. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Use the <sgmltag class="element">vmnic</sgmltag> element
              to setup the virtual network interface. Multiple
              <sgmltag class="element">vmnic</sgmltag> child elements may be
              specified to setup multiple virtual network interfaces.</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">driver</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The mandatory <sgmltag class="attribute"
                      >driver</sgmltag> attribute specifies the driver
                    to be used for the virtual network card. The
                    supported values are <sgmltag class="attvalue"
                      >e100</sgmltag>, <sgmltag class="attvalue"
                      >vlance</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag class="attvalue"
                      >vmxnet</sgmltag>. If the vmxnet driver is
                    specified the vmware tools must be installed in the
                    image. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
                  >interface</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The mandatory <sgmltag class="attribute"
                      >interface</sgmltag> attribute specifies the
                    interface number. If only one interface is set the
                    value should be set to 0. </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><sgmltag class="attribute">mode</sgmltag></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para> The network mode used to communicate outside
                    the VM. In many cases the bridged mode is used.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.users">
      <title><sgmltag>users</sgmltag> Element</title>

      <screen>&lt;users group="group_name" id="number"&gt; 
  &lt;user home="dir" id="number" name="user" password="..."
        pwdformat="encrypted|plain" realname="string" shell="path"/&gt;
  <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> ... </sgmltag>
&lt;/users&gt;</screen>

      <para>The optional <sgmltag>users</sgmltag> element lists the users belonging to the
        group specified with the <sgmltag class="attribute">group</sgmltag> attribute. At least one user
        child element must be specified as part of the <sgmltag>users</sgmltag> element.
        Multiple users elements may be specified. </para>

      <para>The attributes <sgmltag class="attribute">home</sgmltag>,
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
          class="attribute">name</sgmltag>, <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >pwd</sgmltag>, <sgmltag class="attribute">realname</sgmltag>,
        and <sgmltag class="attribute">shell</sgmltag> specify the
        created users home directory, the user name, the user’s
        password, the user’s real name, and the user’s login shell,
        respectively. By default, the value of the password attribute is
        expected to be an encrypted string. An encrypted password can be
        created using <command>kiwi</command>
        <option>--createpassword</option>. It is also possible to
        specify the password as a non encrypted string by using the
        pwdformat attribute and setting it’s value to
          <quote>plain</quote>. KIWI will then encrypt the password
        prior to the user being added to the system. </para>

      <para>All specified users and groups will be created if they do
        not already exist. By default, the defined users will be part of
        the group specified with the group attribute of the users
        element and the default group called <quote>users</quote>. If it
        is desired to have the specified users to only be part of the
        given group it is necessary to specify the <sgmltag
          class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute. It is recommended to
        use a group id greater than 100. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.drivers">
      <title><sgmltag>drivers</sgmltag> Element</title>
      <screen>&lt;drivers profiles="name"&gt; 
  &lt;file name="filename"/&gt; 
  <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> ... </sgmltag> 
&lt;/drivers&gt;</screen>

      <para>The optional <sgmltag>drivers</sgmltag> element is only
        useful for boot images (initrd). As a boot image doesn’t need to
        contain the complete kernel one can save a lot of space if only
        the required drivers are part of the image. Therefore the
        drivers section exists. If present only the drivers which
        matches the file names or glob patterns will be included into
        the boot image. Each file is specified relative to the
        <filename class="directory">/lib/modules/<replaceable>Version</replaceable>/kernel</filename> directory.</para>

      <para>According to the <sgmltag>driver</sgmltag> element the
        specified files are searched in the corresponding directory. The
        information about the driver names is provided as environment
        variable named like the value of the <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >type</sgmltag> attribute and is processed by the function
          <function>suseStripKernel</function>. According to this along
        with a boot image description a script called
          <command>images.sh</command> must exist which calls this
        function in order to allow the driver information to have any
        effect. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.repository">
      <title><sgmltag>repository</sgmltag> Element</title>
      <screen>&lt;repository type="type" alias="name" imageinclude="true|false"
              password="password" priority="number" status="replaceable"
              username="user-name"&gt; &lt;source path="URL"/&gt;
&lt;/repository&gt;</screen>

      <para>The mandatory <sgmltag class="element">repository</sgmltag> element
        specifies the location and type of a repository to be used by the 
        package manager as a package installation source. The mandatory
        <sgmltag class="attribute">type</sgmltag> attribute
        specifies the repository type. A specified repository can only be
        accessed by the chosen package manager if the given type is supported
        by the specified package manager. KIWI supports smart or zypper as
        package managers, specified with the <sgmltag class="element">
        packagemanager</sgmltag> element. The default package manager is
        zypper. The following table shows the possible 
        supported repository types for each package manager:</para>

      <table id="tab.description.supported-types">
        <title>Supported package manager repo types</title>
        <tgroup cols="5">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Type</entry>
              <entry>smart</entry>
              <entry>zypper</entry>
              <entry>apt</entry>
              <entry>yum</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>apt-deb</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>rpm-dir</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>rpm-md</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>yast2</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>yes</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
              <entry>no</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>The <sgmltag class="element">repository</sgmltag> element
        has the following optional attributes: </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">alias</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">name</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies an alternative name for the configured
              repository. If the attribute is not specified KIWI will generate
              an alias name by replacing any <quote>/</quote> in the given 
              repository location with an <quote>_</quote>. It is helpful to
              set an alias name if the repository path is insufficient in
              expressing the purpose of the contained packages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">imageinclude</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">true|false</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies whether the given repository should be configured
              as a repository in the image or not. The default behavior is
              that repositories used to build an image are not configured
              as a repository inside the image. This feature allows you to
              change the behavior by setting the value to <sgmltag
              class="attvalue">true</sgmltag>. The repository is configured
              in the image according to the source path as specified with the
              <sgmltag class="attribute">path</sgmltag> attribute of the
              <sgmltag class="element">source</sgmltag> element. Therefore,
              if the path is not a fully qualified URL, you may need to adjust
              the repository file in the image to accomodate the expected
              location. It is recommended that you use the
              <sgmltag class="attribute">alias</sgmltag> attribute in
              combination with the
              <sgmltag class="attribute">imageinclude</sgmltag> attribute to
              avoid having unpredictable random names assigned to the
              repository you wish to include in the image. This also
              facilitates modification of the "baseurl" entry in the .repo
              file from the config.sh script if you need to make adjustments
              to the path.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
           <term><sgmltag class="attribute">password</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">string</sgmltag>"</term>
           <listitem>
             <para>Specifies a password for the given repository. The
               <sgmltag class="attribute">password</sgmltag> attribute must
               be used in combination with the <sgmltag class="attribute">
               username</sgmltag> attribute. Dependent on the
               repository location this information may not be used.
             </para>
           </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><sgmltag class="attribute">prefer-license</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
        class="attvalue">true|false</sgmltag>"</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>The repository providing this attribute will be used
        primarly to install the license tarball if found on that
        repository. If no repository with a prefered license attribute
        exists, the search happens over all repositories. It's not
        guaranteed in that case that the search order follows the
        repository order like they are written into the XML
        description.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">priority</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">number</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specifies the repository priority for this given repository.
              Priority values are treated differently by different package
              managers. Repository priorities allow the package management
              system to disambiguate packages that may be contained in more
              than one of the configured repositories. The smart package
              manager treats packages from repositories with the 
              <emphasis>highest</emphasis> priority number as preferable to
              packages from a repository with a lower priority number.
              The value 0 means <quote>no priority is set</quote>. The
              zypper package manager prefers packages from a repository with 
              a <emphasis>lower</emphasis> priority over packages from
              a repository with higher priority values. The value 99 means
              <quote>no priority is set</quote>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attribute">status</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">replaceable</sgmltag>"</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This attribute should only be applied in the context of a
              boot image description. Setting the <sgmltag class="attribute">
              status</sgmltag> to <sgmltag class="attvalue">replaceable
              </sgmltag> indicates that the specified repository my be
              replaced by the repositories specified in the image description.
              This is important as the KIWI generated boot image, if required,
              should be created based on packages from the same repositories
              used to build the system image.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
           <term><sgmltag class="attribute">username</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
              class="attvalue">name</sgmltag>"</term>
           <listitem>
             <para>Specifies a user name for the given repository. The
               <sgmltag class="attribute">username</sgmltag> attribute must
               be used in combination with the <sgmltag class="attribute">
               password</sgmltag> attribute. Dependent on the
               repository location this information may not be used.
             </para>
           </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>When specifying an https location for a repository it is
        generally necessary to include the <quote>openssl-certs</quote> and
        <quote>cracklib-dict-full</quote> packages in the 
        <sgmltag class="attvalue">bootstrap</sgmltag> section of the
        image configuration.</para>
      
      <para>The location of a repository is specified by the 
        <sgmltag class="attribute">path</sgmltag> attribute of the
        mandatory <sgmltag class="element">source</sgmltag> child element.
        The location specification may include the
        <systemitem class="macro">%arch</systemitem> macro which will expand
        to the architecture of the image building host. The value for the 
        <sgmltag class="attribute">path</sgmltag> attribute may begin with
        any of the following location indicators:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>dir:///local/path</uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>An absolute path to a directory accessible through the
              local file system. The <quote>dir://</quote> prefix may
              be omitted.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>ftp://<replaceable>URL</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A ftp protocol based network location. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>http://<replaceable>URL</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A http protocol based network location. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>https://<replaceable>URL</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A https protocol based network location. See the comment
              above about the handling of certificates and additional
              package requirements in the <sgmltag class="attvalue">bootstrap
              </sgmltag> section of the image configuration.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>iso://<replaceable>path/to/isofile</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>An absolute path to an .iso file accessible via the local
              file system. KIWI will loop mount the the .iso file to a
              KIWI created directory with a generated name. The generated path
              is provided to the specified package manager as a repository
              location.</para>
            <para>Using multiple .iso files from the same SLE product, requires
              that all .iso files are located in the same directory. Only
              the first .iso file is to be specified as a repository in
              the <filename>config.xml</filename>. The first .iso file
              contains all information necessary for the package manager to
              locate packages that are contained in other .iso files of the
              same product. Attempting to use multiple .iso files
              in a series as standalone repositories will result in an
              error.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>obs://$dir1/$dir2</uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A special network location used with the http protocol.
                The values of <varname>$dir1</varname> and 
                <varname>$dir2</varname> represent the project location in the 
                openSUSE build service. The location is evaluated as
                <uri>this://repos/$dir1/$dir2</uri>.</para>
            <para>The <quote>obs://</quote> prefix is also valid as part
              of the value for the <sgmltag class="attribute">boot</sgmltag>
              attribute of the <sgmltag class="element">type</sgmltag>. If
              used with the <sgmltag class="attribute">boot</sgmltag>
              attribute it is evaluated as
              <uri>this://images/$dir1/$dir2</uri>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>opensuse://<replaceable>PROJECTNAME</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A special network location used with the http protocol. The
              given <replaceable>PROJECTNAME</replaceable> specifies a
              project in the openSUSE buildservice. The repository is a
              repository of type <sgmltag class="attvalue">rpm-md</sgmltag>.
              For example: <sgmltag class="attribute">path</sgmltag>=
              <sgmltag class="attvalue">"opensuse://openSUSE:10.3/standard"
              </sgmltag>. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>plain://<replaceable>URI</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A plain resource string. Everything following 'plain://'
             will be forwarded to the package manager without further
             modification. This type of location specification is useful when
             KIWI does not support a specific URI but the specified package
             manager does.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>smb://<replaceable>Samba share pathname</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>A path to a samba share using the cifs protocol. KIWI
              creates a mount point and mounts the share including username
              and password, if specified. Access to the smb share from within
              the new root tree is provided via a cifs mount. Therefore, 
              the package providing the cifs tools must be included in the
              package list for the <sgmltag class="attvalue">bootstrap
              </sgmltag> section of the image configuration. At the time of
              this writing the package providing the cifs tools is called
              <emphasis>cifs-utils</emphasis>. If any packages provided by the
              Samba share are used as part of the boot image the cifs tools
              must also be included in the boot image. This is accomplished
              with the <sgmltag class="attribute">bootinclude</sgmltag>
              attribute of the <sgmltag class="element">package</sgmltag>
              element. This is shown in the example below:</para>

<screen>&lt;packages type="bootstrap"&gt;
  &lt;package name="cifs-utils" bootinclude="true"/&gt;
  &lt;/packages&gt;</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><uri>this://<replaceable>PATH</replaceable></uri></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><replaceable>PATH</replaceable> is the relative location to
              the image description directory for the curent image.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.description.packages">
      <title><sgmltag>packages</sgmltag> Element</title>
      <screen>&lt;packages type="type" profiles="name" patternType="type"
   &lt;package name="name" arch="arch"/&gt; 
   &lt;package name="name" replaces="name"/&gt;
   &lt;package name="name" bootinclude="true" bootdelete="true"/&gt; 
   &lt;archive name="name" bootinclude="true"/&gt; 
   &lt;package .../&gt; 
   &lt;namedCollection name="name"/&gt; 
   &lt;namedCollection .../&gt;
   &lt;opensuseProduct name="name"/&gt; 
   &lt;opensuseProduct .../&gt; 
   &lt;ignore name="name"/&gt; 
   &lt;ignore .../&gt;
&lt;/packages&gt;</screen>

      <para>The mandatory <sgmltag>packages</sgmltag> element specifies
        the list of packages (element <sgmltag>package</sgmltag>) and
        patterns (element <sgmltag>namedCollection</sgmltag>) to be used
        with the image. The value of the <sgmltag class="attribute"
          >type</sgmltag> attribute specifies how the packages and
        patterns listed are handled, supported values are as follows: </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">bootstrap</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Bootstrap packages, list of packages for the new
              operating system root tree. The packages list the required
              components to support a chroot environment in the new
              system root tree, such as glibc. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">delete</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Delete packages, list of packages to be deleted from
              the image being created. </para>
            <para>When using the delete type only
                <sgmltag>package</sgmltag> elements are considered, all
              other specifications such as
                <sgmltag>namedCollection</sgmltag> are ignored. The
              given package names are stored in the
                $<envar>delete</envar> environment variable of the
                <filename>/.profile</filename> file created by KIWI. The
              list of package names is returned by the
                <function>baseGetPackagesForDeletion</function>
              function. This list can then be used to delete the
              packages ignoring requirements or dependencies. This can
              be accomplished in the <command>config.sh</command> or
                <command>images.sh</command> script by calling the following
              helper function: </para>
            <screen><command>suseRemovePackagesMarkedForDeletion</command></screen>
            <para>Note, that the delete value is indiscriminate of the
              image type being built. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">image</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Image packages, list of packages to be installed in
              the image. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">iso</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Image packages, a list of additional packages to be
              installed when building an ISO image. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">oem</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Image packages, a list of additional packages to be
              installed when building an OEM image. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">pxe</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Image packages, a list of additional packages to be
              installed when building an PXE image. </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><sgmltag class="attvalue">vmx</sgmltag></term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Image packages, a list of additional packages to be
              installed when building a vmx virtual image of any format.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <sect3 id="sec.descriptions.using-patterns">
        <title>Using Patterns</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>KIWI</primary>
          <secondary>patterns</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para> Using a pattern name allows you to considerably shorten
          the list of specified packages in the <filename>config.xml</filename>
          file. A named pattern, specified with the <sgmltag
            class="element">namedCollection</sgmltag> element is a
          representation of a predefined list of packages. Specifying a
          pattern will install all packages listed in the named pattern to be
          installed in the image. Support for patterns is distribution specific
          and available with SLES, openSUSE, CentOS and RHEL. The
          optional <sgmltag class="attribute">patternType</sgmltag> attribute
          on the 
          <sgmltag class="element">packages</sgmltag> element allows you to
          control the installation of dependent packages in the image.
          You may assigne one of the following values to the
          <sgmltag class="attribute">patternType</sgmltag> attribute:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="attribute">onlyRequired</sgmltag></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Incorporates only patterns and packages that
               the specifeid patterns and packages require. This is
               a "hard dependency" only resolution.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><sgmltag class="attribute"
              >plusRecommended</sgmltag></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Incorporates patterns and packages that are required
               and recommended by the specified patterns and packages
               in <filename>config.xml</filename>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>By default, only required patterns and packages are installed.
          KIWI depends on the package manager to resolve the specified list
          of patterns and packages against the specified repositories and
          complete the installation. Note that not all supported package
          managers support the use of named patterns, thus the value of the
          <sgmltag class="element">packageManager</sgmltag> element
          determines whether you are able to use named patterns or not.
          Should the list of specified packages result in a conflict the
          image creation process will stop and the information provided by
          the package manager will be captured in the build log and will be
          displayed in the terminal window where KIWI was started. The
          <sgmltag class="element">ignore</sgmltag> element may be of use
          in resolving such conflicts. However, the <sgmltag
            class="element">ignore</sgmltag> element is limited to effect
          packages named explicitely. Packages installed in the image through
          a named pattern are not effected by the <sgmltag
           class="element">ignore</sgmltag> element setting. THerefore,
          package conflicts created by packages within named patterns cannot
          be resolved using the ignore mechanism. Further, if a package is
          specified to be ignored, but is required by another package, then
          the required package is installed in the image via the automatic
          dependency resolution by the package manager in use.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="sec.description.architecture-restrictions">
        <title>Architecture Restrictions</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>KIWI</primary>
          <secondary>architecture restrictions</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para> To restrict a package to a specific architecture, use the
          arch attribute to specify a comma separated list of allowed
          architectures. Such a package is only installed if the build
          systems architecture (<command>uname</command>
          <option>-m</option>) matches one of the specified values of
          the arch attribute. </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.description.packages.to.become.included">
        <title>Packages to Become Included Into the Boot Image</title>
        <para> The optional attributes bootinclude and bootdelete can be
          used to mark a package inside the system image description to
          become part of the corresponding boot image (initrd). This
          feature is most often used to specify bootsplash and/or
          graphics boot related packages inside the system image
          description but they are required to be part of the boot image
          as the data is used at boot time of the image.</para>
        <para>Packages included into the boot image with the <sgmltag
          class="attribute">bootinclude</sgmltag> are still included into
          the system image as well. If packages should only be included into
          the boot image, but not the system image, they need to be added to
          the <sgmltag class="element">packages</sgmltag> section of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">type</sgmltag>=<sgmltag
          class="attvalue">delete</sgmltag>.</para>
        <para>If the
          bootdelete attribute is specified along with the bootinclude
          attribute this means that the selected package will be marked
          as a <quote>to become deleted</quote> package and is removed
          by the contents of the <command>images.sh</command> script of
          the corresponding boot image description.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.description.data.not.available">
        <title>Data not Available as Packages to Become Included</title>
        <para> With the optional <sgmltag>archive</sgmltag> element it’s
          possible to include any kind of data into the image. The
          archive elements expects the name of a tarball which must
          exist as part of the system image description. KIWI then picks
          up the tarball and installs it into the image. If the
          bootinclude attribute is set along with the archive element
          the data will also become installed into the boot image.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
