<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="chap.oem">
 <title>OEM Image / Preload Systems</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KIWI</primary>
 <secondary>OEM image</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>images</primary>
 <secondary>OEM</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>OEM images</primary></indexterm>
 <para>
  An OEM image is a virtual disk image representing all partitions and
  bootloader information the same way as on a physical disk. All flavors
  discussed previously in <xref linkend="chap.vmx"/> also apply to the OEM
  image type. Compared to the VMX image type, an OEM image comes with
  additional features. It is able to expand itself to a custom disk geometry
  and KIWI can create installation images which embeds the OEM image for
  deployment from CD/DVD/Stick and over the network via PXE.
 </para>
 <indexterm>
 <primary>Installation</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>USB Stick</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>DVD</primary></indexterm>
 <para>
  The basic idea behind an OEM image is to provide the virtual disk data for
  OEM vendors to support easy deployment of the system to physical storage
  media.
 </para>

 <tip>
  <title>OEM Image Description Templates</title>
  <para>
   &template_intro;
  </para>
  <para>
   OEM image templates are shipped with the package
   <package>kiwi-desc-oemboot</package>. They are installed to
   <filename>/usr/share/kiwi/image/oemboot</filename>.
  </para>
 </tip>


 <sect1 id="sec.oem.building">
  <title>Building an OEM System and an Installation Image</title>

  <para>
   The image creation process creates two images: An OEM disk image and an
   Installation ISO image containing the OEM disk image. The disk image can be
   dumped on a physical disk on the target system (using for example
   <command>dd</command>). The installation image can be dumped or burned
   to a bootable installation medium (for example a flash disk or a DVD).
   When a machine is booted from such a medium, an image deployment process
   (which can optionally be configured to run without user interaction) is
   started. The following example shows how to build a Just enough Operating
   System (JeOS) based on SUSE Linux Enterprise 12:
  </para>

 <screen><command>kiwi</command> --build suse-SLE12-JeOS -d /tmp/myoem-result --type oem</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.oem.testing">
  <title>Testing the Images</title><indexterm>

  <primary>raw</primary>

  <secondary>file name extension</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>iso</primary>

  <secondary>file name extension</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   The images can be tested using virtualization software such as QEMU,
   VMware, or VirtualBox. The OEM disk image file can b identified by the
   extension <filename class="extension">.raw</filename>, the installation
   image either has the <filename class="extension">.iso</filename> or the
   <filename class="extension">.raw.install</filename> extension (also see
   <xref linkend="sec.oem.flavours"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
   To test the OEM disk image using <command>qemu</command>, run the
   following commands:
  </para>

  <screen>cd /tmp/myoem-result
qemu LimeJeOS-SLE12.x86_64-1.13.1.raw</screen>

  <para>
   Alternatively, use the <command>dd</command> command to dump the image onto
   a spare hard disk or a flash disk (this will wipe all existing data on the
   target device). To boot the image, select the appropriate device
   for booting device in the BIOS/EFI.
  </para>

<screen>cd /tmp/myoem-result
dd if=LimeJeOS-SLE12.x86_64-1.13.1.raw of=/dev/<replaceable>device</replaceable></screen>

<!--
  <note>
   <title>Retaining the Disk Geometry</title>
   <para>
    When deploying the OEM image with <command>dd</command> the geometry of
    the disk image is not changed therefore retains the disk geometry of the
   host system. The change is made during the initialboot of the image&mdash;
   </para>
  </note
-->
  <para>
   Note, when testing an oem image using the virtual disk image, i.e. the
   <filename class="extension">.raw</filename> file, the geometry of the
   disk image is not changed and therefore retains the disk geometry of the
   host system. This implies that the re-partitioning performed for a
   physical disk install during the oem boot workflow will be skipped.

   <remark condition="clarity">
    2015-11-30 - fs: Does this mean you are asked whether you want to perform
    the repartitioning or not during the initial boot process?
   </remark>
  </para>

  <para>
   The installation image can also be tested using virtualization
   software. Note that the hard disk will be re-partitioned in this case. The
   following example uses <command>qemu</command> for testing. A virtual hard
   disk is created with <command>qemu-img</command> prior to starting the
   image.
  </para>

  <screen>cd /tmp/myoem-result
qemu-img create /tmp/mydisk 20G
qemu -hda /tmp/mydisk -cdrom LimeJeOS-SLE12.x86_64-1.13.1.iso -boot d</screen>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="sec.oem.flavours">
  <title>Installation Image Flavours</title>

  <para>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>installiso</primary>
    </indexterm> <indexterm>
    <primary>installstick</primary>
   </indexterm>
   The installation image is a bootable, self-installing image that deploys
   the OEM image onto the selected storage device. The installation process is
   a simple image dump using the <command>dd</command> command. During this
   process the target system remains in terminal mode.
  </para>
  <para>
   The installation image can be created in two formats: a hybrid image
   suitable for CD/DVD media and flsh disks and a second one suitable for a
   flash disks only. The latter format can be used if the BIOS/EFI does not
   support booting from hybrif images.  The following
   configuration snippets show the use of the <sgmltag
   class="attribute">installiso</sgmltag> to create a CD/DVD iso image and
   <sgmltag class="attribute">installstick</sgmltag> attributes in
   <filename>configuration.xml</filename> to create an USB installation image
   format.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>installiso</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Creates an <filename class="extension">.iso</filename> file which can be
      burned onto a CD or a DVD or dumped on a flash disk. The attribute
      <sgmltag class="attribute">hybrid="true"</sgmltag> makes sure a hybrid
      iso image is created that is suitable for both purposes. A
      hybrid image is the recommended format for an installation image. If the
      target hardware is not able to boot from such an image, try the <sgmltag
      class="attribute">installstick</sgmltag> variant described below.
     </para>
     <screen>&lt;image ...&gt;
  &lt;preferences&gt;
    ...
    &lt;type image="name" installiso="true" hybrid="true" ....&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/type&gt;
  &lt;/preferences&gt;
  ...
&lt;/image ...&gt;</screen>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <literal>installstick</literal>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Creates a <filename class="extension">.raw.install</filename> file
      which can be dumped (<command>dd</command>) onto a USB stick. Use this
      format if your machine canmnot boot from a hybrid image.
     </para>
     <screen>&lt;image ...&gt;
  &lt;preferences&gt;
    ...
    &lt;type image="name" installstick="true" ....&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/type&gt;
  &lt;/preferences&gt;
  ...
&lt;/image ...&gt;</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.oem.customize">
  <title>Customizinge the OEM Images</title>
  <para>
   KIWI not only allows to customize the boot process of an OEM image by
   adding scripts to the image but also provides many configuration options
   that let you customize the boot loader, partitioning and other aspects of
   the image.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.oem.customize.installation">
   <title>Customizing the OEM Install Process</title><indexterm>
   <primary>preHWdetect.sh</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>postHWdetect.sh</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>preImageDump.sh</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>postImageDump.sh</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    It is possible to customize the OEM install process by providing shell
    scripts with the following names. For more information on how to include
    the scripts into the boot image and make them work in the boot code, see
    the chapter <xref linkend="sec.hooks"/>.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>preHWdetect.sh</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This script is executed prior to the hardware scan on the target
       machine.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>postHWdetect.sh</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This script is executed after the hardware scan on the target machine.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>preImageDump.sh</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This script is executed immediately prior to the OEM image dump onto
       the target storage device.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><filename>postImageDump.sh</filename></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This script is executed directly after the OEM image dump onto the
       target storage device once the image checksum has been successfully
       verified.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.oem.customize.parameters">
   <title>OEM Customizing Parameters</title>
   <para>
    <remark condition="clarity">
     2015-12-01 - fs: oem-home* is/are? missing. Any others?
    </remark>
    All OEM customizing parameters reside in the <sgmltag
    class="element">oemconfig</sgmltag> tag in
    <filename>configuration.xml</filename>:
   </para>
   <screen>&lt;image ...&gt;
  &lt;preferences&gt;
    ...
    &lt;type image="oem" ....&gt;
      &lt;oemconfig&gt;
        &lt;oem-.../&gt;
      &lt;/oemconfig&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/type&gt;
  &lt;/preferences&gt;
  ...
&lt;/image ...&gt;</screen>

   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-boot-title</sgmltag
      >text<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-boot-title</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       By default, the string <literal>OEM</literal>> will be used
       as the boot manager menu entry when KIWI creates the GRUB configuration
       during deployment. The <sgmltag>oem-boot-title</sgmltag> element allows
       you to set a custom name for the grub menu entry. This value can also
       be set at the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemtitle="<replaceable>TITLE</replaceable>"</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-bootwait</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-bootwait</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify if the system should wait for user interaction prior to
       continuing the initial boot process after (default value is
       <literal>false</literal>). This value can also be set at the boot
       prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oembootwait=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-inplace-recovery</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-inplace-recovery</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify if the recovery archive is stored as part of the image or if
       the archive is to be created at the time the image is deployed to the
       target storage device. This value can also be set at the boot prompt
       by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemrecoveryInPlace=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-kiwi-initrd</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-kiwi-initrd</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If this element is set to <literal>true</literal> (default value is
       <literal>false</literal>) the oemboot boot image (initrd) will
       <emphasis>not</emphasis> be replaced by the initrd created by the
       system. This option is useful when the system is installed on flash
       drives. When booting from such a drive it is usually necessary to
       detect the storage location on each boot. This detection process is
       part of the oemboot boot image. This value can also be set at the boot
       prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemkboot=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-partition-install</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-partition-install</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       By default (<literal>false</literal>), an OEM image is installed on the
       specified disk on the target system. During this process the disk is
       being overwritten and the original data is lost. Setting this parameter
       to <literal>true</literal>, installs the image into an empty partition
       (that is a partition without a file system). If the device already
       contains a swap partition, it will be used, otherwise a swap file will
       be created. The empty partition needs to exist prior to booting the
       KIWI image, otherwise the installation will fail. Setting this
       parameter to <literal>true</literal> also makes KIWI ignore any other
       partitioning-related setting (for example <sgmltag
       class="element">oem-swap</sgmltag>). See <xref
       linkend="sec.oem.partition-based-installation"/> for more details. This
       value can also be set at the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oempartition_install=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-reboot</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-reboot</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If set to <literal>true</literal>, the system reboots after the OEM
       image has been deployed. By default this parameter si set to
       <literal>false</literal>. This value can also be set at the boot prompt
       by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemreboot=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-reboot-interactive</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-reboot-interactive</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If set to <literal>true</literal>, the system reboots after the OEM
       image has been deployed. A message, which the user has to confirm to
       start the reboot is displayed. By default this parameter is set to
       <literal>false</literal>. This value can also be set at the boot prompt
       by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemrebootinteractive=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-recovery</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-recovery</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If this element is set to <literal>true</literal> (default value is
       <literal>false</literal>), KIWI will create a recovery archive from the
       prepared root tree. The archive will appear as
       <filename>/recovery.tar.bz2</filename> in the image file. During the
       first boot of the image a single recovery partition will be created and
       the recovery archive will be moved to that partition. A boot menu entry
       for recovery, that will restores the original root tree on the system,
       is created. User data stored in <filename
       class="directory">/home</filename> will not be affected by the recovery
       process. This value can also be set at the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemrecovery=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-recoveryID</sgmltag
       >partition-id<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-recoveryID</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify the partition type for the recovery partition. The default is
       to create a Linux partition (id = 83). This value can also be set at
       the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemrecoveryID=<replaceable>ID</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-silent-boot</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-silent-boot</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify if the system should show boot messages
       (<literal>false</literal>) on the very first boot after having deployed
       the OEM image, or whether all boot messages should be suppressed
       (<literal>true</literal>). This value can also be set at the boot
       prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemsilentboot=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-shutdown</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-shutdown</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify if the system is to be powered down after the OEM image has
       been deployed (the default value is <literal>false</literal>). This
       value can also be set at the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemshutdown=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-shutdown-interactive</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-shutdown-interactive</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify if the system is to be powered down after the OEM image has
       been deployed. A message, which the user has to confirm to start the
       shutdown process, is displayed. This value can also be set at the boot
       prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemshutdowninteractive=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-swap</sgmltag
       >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-swap</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specify if a swap partition should be created (the default is
       <literal>true</literal>). This value can also be set at the boot prompt
       by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemswap=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <sgmltag class="starttag">oem-swapsize</sgmltag
       >size in MB<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-swapsize</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set the size of the swap partition in megabytes. If a swap partition is
       to be created and the size of the swap partition is not specified with
       this optional element, KIWI will create a swap partition of a size
       equal to two times of the RAM size at initial boot time. This value can
       also be set at the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemswapMB=<replaceable>SIZE_IN_MB</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><sgmltag class="starttag">oem-systemsize</sgmltag
      >size in MB<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-systemsize</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set the size the operating system is allowed to consume on the target
       disk. The size limit does not include any consideration for swap space
       or a recovery partition. In a setup <emphasis>without</emphasis> a
       <sgmltag class="element">systemdisk</sgmltag> element this value
       specifies the size of the root partition. In a setup
       <emphasis>including</emphasis> a <sgmltag
       class="element">systemdisk</sgmltag> element this value specifies the
       size of the LVM partition which contains all specified volumes. Thus,
       the sum of all specified volume sizes plus the sum of the specified
       free space for each volume must be smaller or equal than the size
       specified with the <sgmltag
       class="element">oem-systemsize</sgmltag>. This value can also be set at
       the boot prompt by the parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemrootMB=<replaceable>SIZE_IN_MB</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><sgmltag class="starttag">oem-unattended</sgmltag
      >true|false<sgmltag class="endtag">oem-unattended</sgmltag>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If set to <literal>true</literal>, the image deployment is done without
       requiring user interaction. If the target system contains multiple
       disks, the first device (/dev/sda, for example) is automatically
       selected. This value can also be set at the boot prompt by the
       parameter
       <literal>kiwi_oemunattended=<replaceable>TRUE_OR_FALSE</replaceable></literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.oem.partition-based-installation">
   <title>Partition Based Installation</title><indexterm>
   <primary>config.xml</primary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The default installation method of an OEM image is to dump the entire
    virtual disk onto the target disk and to re-partition the disk to match
    the real geometry. All data that was previously stored on the disk will be
    erased.
   </para>
   <para>
    Alternatively KIWI supports the installation into already existing
    partitions. This requires to set up <emphasis>empty</emphasis> (no file
    system) partitions prior to deploying the image. This way already existing
    data will not be touched. To activate the partition based install mode the
    following option has to be set in <filename>config.xml</filename>:
   </para>
   <screen>&lt;image ...&gt;
  &lt;preferences&gt;
    ...
    &lt;type image="oem" ....&gt;
      &lt;oemconfig&gt;
        &lt;oem-partition-install&gt;true&lt;/oem-partition-install&gt;
      &lt;/oemconfig&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/type&gt;
  &lt;/preferences&gt;
  ...
&lt;/image ...&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    With a partition-based installation, the setup differs from the default,
    disk-based installation in the following ways:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The bootloader will be set up to boot the installed system only. If a
      multi-boot setup is required, it needs to be manually configured by the
      user after the initial boot.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The parameter <sgmltag class="element">oem-home*</sgmltag>, <sgmltag
      class="element">oem-swap*</sgmltag>, and <sgmltag
      class="element">oem-systemsize</sgmltag> for system, swap and home are
      ignored. In this mode KIWI will not create additional partitions. If a
      swap partition exists, it will automatically be used, if not, a
      swap-file will be created.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      There is no support for a remote (PXE) OEM installation, because KIWI
      has to loop-mount the disk image and need to address specific regions
      inside of the image. Such operations are not implemented for remote
      access
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.oem.pxe-based-installation">
  <title>Network Based Installation</title><indexterm>
  <primary>network installation</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>installation</primary>
  <secondary>network</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   Instead of manually dumping the OEM image on the target device or creating
   a KIWI installation CD or flash disk, the image can alternatively be
   downloaded from a PXE boot server over the network. This requires a PXE
   network boot server to be setup as explained in <xref
   linkend="chap.pxe"/>. If your PXE server is running the following steps are
   required to setup the installation process over the network:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make sure to create an installation PXE tarball along with your OEM
     image by setting the following option in
     <filename>configuration.xml</filename>:
    </para>
    <screen>&lt;image ...&gt;
  &lt;preferences&gt;
    ...
    &lt;type image="oem" installpxe="true"....&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/type&gt;
  &lt;/preferences&gt;
  ...
&lt;/image ...&gt;</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create the image, unpack the resulting
     <filename><replaceable>IMAGE_NAME</replaceable>.tgz</filename> file to a
     temporary directory and copy the <filename>initrd</filename> and
     kernel images to the PXE server:
    </para>
    <screen>
      mkdir /tmp/pxe &amp;&amp; cd /tmp/pxe
      <command>tar</command> -xf <replaceable>PATH_TO</replaceable>/<replaceable>IMAGE_NAME</replaceable>.tgz
<command>scp</command> initrd-oemboot-*.install.* <replaceable>PXE_SERVER_IP</replaceable>:/srv/tftpboot/boot/initrd
<command>scp</command> initrd-oemboot-*.kernel.*  <replaceable>PXE_SERVER_IP</replaceable>:/srv/tftpboot/boot/linux</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Also copy the system image and the md5 sum to to the PXE boot server:
    </para>
    <screen><command>scp</command> <replaceable>IMAGE_FILE</replaceable>.xz  <replaceable>PXE_SERVER_IP</replaceable>:/srv/tftpboot/image/
<command>scp</command> <replaceable>IMAGE_FILE</replaceable>.md5 <replaceable>PXE_SERVER_IP</replaceable>:/srv/tftpboot/image/</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Copy the kernel commandline parameters from
     <filename><replaceable>IMAGE_FILE</replaceable>.append</filename>. Edit
     your PXE configuration (for example
     <filename>pxelinux.cfg/default</filename>) on the PXE server and add
     these parameters to the append line.
    </para>
    <para>
     Optionally the image and it's md5sum can be stored on a FTP or HTTP
     server specified via the parameters
     <command>kiwiserver=<replaceable>IP_ADRESS</replaceable></command> and
     <command>kiwiservertype=<replaceable>HTTP_HTTPS_OR_FTP</replaceable></command>. In
     this case make sure to copy the system image and md5 file to the correct
     location on the server. KIWI searches the image at
     <replaceable>SERVER_ROOT</replaceable>/image (for example
     http://www.example.com/image/<replaceable>IMAGE_FILE</replaceable>.xz). Note
     that initrd and linux kernel are always loaded via PXE.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
