<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<sect1 id="chap.raid">
 <title>KIWI RAID Support</title><indexterm>
 <primary>KIWI</primary>
 <secondary>RAID</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  KIWI supports three types of RAID systems:
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Real RAID Controllers with Their Own Firmware</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     KIWI only needs to make sure the drivers are part of the initrd e.g cciss
     for the smart array controllers built into some server boards.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>BIOS RAID Controllers</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Cheap onboard controller devices with the RAID software inside the BIOS
     (so called fake RAID). Linux supports some of them with the 'dmraid'
     utility and the support is a mix of BIOS calls and some device mapper
     calls.
    </para>
    <para>
     The check for these devices can be switched on and off with
     &lt;oem-ataraid-scan&gt;true|false&lt;/oem-ataraid-scan&gt;
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Linux Software RAID</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     There is no hardware involved. The Linux kernel can control any storage
     device by adding RAID capabilities. All the work done by a real
     hardware controller is done in software.
    </para>
    <para>
     All this is done using the 'mdadm' utility. The metadata for the
     devices are stored in RAID blocks on the storage device which requires
     them to be of the correct partition type.
    </para>
    <para>
     The software RAID is supported in a so called degraded mode. This means
     the RAID is created but not all devices to build it are attached. That is
     because an image initially only consists of a single disk. The user needs
     to add devices or change the RAID mode manually after deployment. This is
     an easy task if the system comes up prepared accordingly. To use
     Linux software raid in KIWI images you only need to set:
    </para>
    <para>
     &lt;type ... mdraid="mirroring"&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
     Currently kiwi supports a degraded mirroring (raid:1) or stripping
     (raid:0) configuratiom but you can change the mode to any supported raid
     level after deployment.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</sect1>
