<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.lxc">
  <title>Linux Container</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>Container image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>images</primary>
    <secondary>lxc</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Container image</primary>
    <secondary>lxc image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para><ulink url="http://lxc.sourceforge.net/">
      <citetitle>Linux Containers (LXC)</citetitle></ulink> provide operating
       system-level virtualization, utilizing
      <ulink url="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/cgroups/cgroups.txt">
	      <citetitle>Control Groups (cgroups)</citetitle></ulink>. The
      virtualization is similar to technologies in OpenVZ, Linux-VServer,
      FreeBSD jails, AIX Workload Partitions, and Solaris Containers. The
      network and process space of the container is separated from the
      host resources using namespaces. Kernel space information is mounted
      into the container root filesystem using the <filename>fstab</filename>
      file in the configuration directory. The container root filesystem
      provides the new user space on top of the running kernel of the host.
      A linux container has two components, the container root file system
      stored in
      <filename class="directory">/var/lib/lxc/<replaceable>CONTAINER_NAME</replaceable></filename>
      and the container configuration stored in
      <filename class="directory">/etc/lxc/<replaceable>CONTAINER_NAME</replaceable></filename>.
      The kiwi created container image is packaged in a tarball containing
      the root filesystem and the configuration. The tarball is expected
      to be inflated at the root level (/) of the target system that
      functions as host.</para>

  <sect1 id="sec.lxc.building">
    <title>Building the suse-lxc-guest Example</title>
    <para>The lxc-guest example provided with KIWI is based on recent
      openSUSE releases, one example configuration per release. The example
      provides a very minimal system.</para>

    <screen><command>cd</command> /usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/examples 
<command>cd</command> suse-...
<command>kiwi</command> --prepare ./suse-lxc-guest --root /tmp/mylxc </screen>

    <screen><command>kiwi</command> --create /tmp/mylxc --type lxc -d /tmp/mylxc-result</screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.lxc.using">
    <title>Using the Image</title>
    <para>The created container is packaged in a tarball in the destination
      directory, <filename class="directory">mylxc-result</filename>
      in the example above. Move this tarball to the root level (/) of
      the host machine and unpack it. The following commands assume that
      the image build machine is also the host machine.</para>

      <screen><command>cp</command> /tmp/mylxc-result/suse-##.#-lxc-guest-lxc.*-1.0.0.tbz /
<command>cd</command> /
<command>tar -xjf</command> suse-##.#-lxc-guest-lxc.*-1.0.0.tbz
<command>lxc-start</command> -n os### -f /etc/lxc/os###/config </screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.lxc.details">
    <title>Image Configuartion Details</title>
    <para>The configuartion for a container does not need to contain a kernel
      package. The container represents the user space that runs on top
      of the kernel of the container host system.</para>
    <para>The container itself must contain the Linux user space container
      tools and thus the <emphasis>lxc</emphasis> package must
      be included in the container image.
    </para>
    <para>Configure the network configuration for the container using the
      <sgmltag class="element">vmnic</sgmltag> element.
      The  <sgmltag class="attribute">mode</sgmltag>
      attribute indicates the network mode, <emphasis>veth</emphasis>
      by default. While it is possible to configure multiple network
      interfaces in the <filename>config.xml</filename> file, the written
      conteiner configuartion will only reflect the information configured
      for the first <sgmltag class="element">vmnic</sgmltag>
      element found in the <filename>config.xml</filename> file. The
      configuration for the container expects that the host has a configured
      network bridge with the name <emphasis>br0</emphasis>.
      For complex network setup implementations it is necessary to edit the
      config file.
    </para>
    <para>The generated configuartion file restricts the device access
      of the container according to a generally accepted best practice
      security  model. The device access permissions may be modified by
      editing the <filename>config</filename> file for the container.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
