<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.ec2">
  <title>EC2 Image—Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>EC2 image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>images</primary>
    <secondary>EC2</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Amazon Elastic Comput Cloud</primary>
    <see>EC2 image</see>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>EC2 images</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>The <trademark>Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud</trademark> (Amazon
    EC2) web service provides you with the ability to execute arbitrary
	applications in the Amazon computing environment. To use Amazon EC2 you
    simply: </para>

  <procedure id="proc.ec2.using">
    <step>
      <para>Create an Amazon Machine Image (AMI) containing all your
        software, including your operating system and associated
        configuration settings, applications, libraries, etc. Such an
        AMI can be created by the KIWI ec2 image format. In order to do
        that KIWI makes use of the tools provided by Amazon. Your build
        system should have these tools installed. Due to license issues
        we are not allowed to distribute the tools which means you need
        to download, install and setup them from here:<ulink
          url="http://aws.amazon.com/documentation/ec2/"/>
		software, including the operating system and associated
        configuration settings, applications, libraries, etc.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>Upload this AMI to the Amazon S3 (Amazon Simple Storage
	   Service) service.
      </para>	
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>Register your AMI with Amazon EC2.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
       <para>
        Use the AMI ID created during registration to run your EC2 guest.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
    <para>
    KIWI creates an AMI using tools provided by Amazon. Due to
    licensing issues it is not possible to distribute the Amazon tools with
    your Linux distribution or KIWI. Amazon provides two sets of tools,
    AMI tools and API tools. The tools can be downloaded from the Amazon
    web site at <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/developertools/368"/> and
    <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/developertools/351"/> respectively.
    The documentation for the command line tools may be accessed on the
    Amazon web-site as well at
    <ulink url="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AWSEC2/latest/CommandLineReference"/>. While KIWI only needs to interact with the AMI tools to create the
    AMI you will also need to install the API tools to interact with EC2.
    You must at least install the AMI tools to create an EC2 image with KIWI.
    </para>
    <para>When working with the Amazon tools it is useful to set the
    EC2_HOME, EC2_PRIVATE_KEY, and EC2_CERT environment variables. Setting
    EC2_PRIVATE_KEY, and EC2_CERT allows you to forego specification of the
    <option>--private-key</option> and <option>--cert</option> with every
    command. The EC@_HOME environment variable is used by the tools to find
    required libraries.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>EC2_HOME</para>
        <para>Location of the bin and lib directories installed by the
            Amazon tools. A good location for the tools on your
            system is <filename>/usr/local</filename>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>EC2_PRIVATE_KEY</para>
        <para>Path to your private key file (including the filename). For
            example <filename>/home/USERNAME/AWS/keys/pk-....pem</filename>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>EC2_CERT</para>
        <para>Path to your certificate file (including the filename). For
            example <filename>/home/USERNAME/AWS/keys/cert-....pem</filename>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Please note that your account will be billed by Amazon at the 
     published rate for any computing resources you consume in EC2. This
     includes but is not limited to, running instances, storing data
     (your image) on S3 or EBS, and network traffic.
    </para>
    
  <sect1 id="sec.ec2.building">
    <title>Building the suse-ec2-guest Example</title>
    <para>The example provided with KIWI uses openSUSE as the base
      distribution and includes the base pattern plus the vim editor.
    </para>
    <para>Before building the EC2 example assure that the EC2 command line
      tools are installed and work as expected. Executing the 
      <command>ec2-describe-images</command> <option>-a</option> command
      should return a list of all available instances in EC2. Further, you
      need to edit the <filename>config.xml</filename> file of the example
      and enter your EC2 account information. Replace the values for
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2accountnr</sgmltag>,
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2privatekeyfile</sgmltag>, and
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2certfile</sgmltag>. Note that the account
      number is displayed with dsahes ('-") on the Amazon web site, but the
      entry in <filename>config.xml</filename> is expected to be numeric only.
      The private key file is the private file you downloaded when you
      created the certificate. It is recommended to create a copy of the
      example <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/examples/suse-<replaceable>Version</replaceable>/suse-ec2-guest</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>You are now ready to build the EC2 example. Lets assume you copied
      the example configuration directory to /tmp prior to modifying the
      <filename>config.xml</filename> file.
    </para>
 
    <screen>
        <command>kiwi</command> --prepare /tmp/suse-ec2-guest --root /tmp/myec2
    </screen>

    <screen>
        <command>kiwi</command> --create /tmp/myec2 -d /tmp/myec2-result -y
    </screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.ec2.using">
    <title>Using the Image</title>
    <para> The generated image needs to be transfered to Amazon. The upload
      of the AMI is performed using the <command>ec2-upload-bundle</command>
      command line tool. This tool is part of the API tools provided by Amazon.
      Upload the AMI as follows, replacing 
      <replaceable>AWS_Key_ID</replaceable> and
      <replaceable>AWS_secret_Key_ID</replaceable> with your Amazon key
      information. Also you may want to choose a different name for your
      bucket than <filename>myImages</filename>. If the bucket does not
      exist in S3 it will be created.
    </para>
    
    <screen><command>ec2-upload-bundle</command> -b<!--
     --> <replaceable>myImages</replaceable> \
        -a <replaceable>AWS_Key_ID</replaceable> -s<!--
     --> <replaceable>AWS_secret_Key_ID</replaceable> -m /tmp/myec2/ \
     suse-11.3-ec2-guest.i686-1.1.2.ec2/ \
     suse-11.3-ec2-guest.i686-1.1.2.ami.manifest.xml
    </screen>

    <para>After the upload process is complete register your image with the
      EC2 infrastructure using the <command>ec2-register</command>
      command as shown below. The result of the registration
      process is an AMI ID returned on the command line in the form
      <quote>ami-</quote> followed by a random key sequence.
    </para>

    <screen><command>ec2-register</command> myImages/<!--
     --> suse-11.3-ec2-guest.i686-1.1.2.ami.manifest.xml </screen>

    <para>Once the image is registered via the <command>ec2-register</command>
      command you can use the AWS management console in your browser to 
      launch an instance of your image. It is alos possible to launch an
      instance from the command line. This process is demonstrated below.
      The <command>ec2-describe-images</command> command will provide you
      with an overview of all your registered images.
    </para>

    <para>Prior to launching your instance from the command line you will need
      to have a keypair. In the Web UI the launch wizard will guide you
      through this process. The command line interface if the
      <command>ec2-add-keypair</command> command. The public/private
      keypair is used to allow you to have access to your instance. If you
      do not already have a keypair for interacting with EC2 images you can
      generate a keypair as shown below. The 
      <replaceable>gsg-keypair</replaceable> name is used in this example,
      but you can choose any name you like. As you will need to use the
      key quite often you probably want a name that is easy to remember
      and not too terribly long to type.
    </para>

    <screen><command>ec2-add-keypair</command> gsg-keypair </screen>

    <para>
      Save the private key returned by the command in a local file.
      Using your favorite text editor, create a file named 
      <filename>id_rsa-gsg-keypair</filename> and paste
      everything between (and including) the <literal>-----BEGIN RSA
      PRIVATE KEY-----</literal> and <literal>-----END RSA PRIVATE
      KEY-----</literal> lines into it. To review your existing
      keypairs use the <command>ec2-describe-keypairs</command> command.
    </para>

    <para>The Amazon EC2 infrastructure uses PVGrub (Para-Virtual Grub) to
      boot instances of an image. Basically Amazon provides a minimal
      Linux kernel that has parts of Grub built in and is specialized
      to EC2. PVGrub at some point looks for and reads the 
      <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename> file in
      your image and then boots the specified kernel. Each availability zone
      in EC2 has it's own independent copy of this boot mechanism. Every boot
      kernel has an ID starting with the TLA (Three Letter Acronym)
      <emphasis>aki</emphasis>. The 
      <xref linkend="tab.ec2.kernel-image-ids" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
      table below provides guidelines for the selection of the AKI ID.

    <table id="tab.ec2.kernel-image-ids">
      <title>Amazon Kernel Image IDs</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Zone</entry>
            <entry>AKI</entry>
            <entry>Arch</entry>
            <entry>Name</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>US-East</entry>
            <entry>aki-407d9529</entry>
            <entry>x86</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-i386.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>US-East</entry>
            <entry>aki-427d952b</entry>
            <entry>x86-64</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>US-West</entry>
            <entry>aki-99a0f1dc</entry>
            <entry>x86</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-us-west-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>US-West</entry>
            <entry>aki-9ba0f1de</entry>
            <entry>x86-64</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-us-west-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>EU-West</entry>
            <entry>aki-4deec439</entry>
            <entry>x86</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-eu/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>EU-West</entry>
            <entry>aki-4feec43b</entry>
            <entry>x86-64</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-eu/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>AP-SouthEast</entry>
            <entry>aki-13d5aa41</entry>
            <entry>x86</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-ap-southeast-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>AP-SouthEast</entry>
            <entry>aki-11d5aa43</entry>
            <entry>x86-64</entry>
            <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-ap-southeast-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.01-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    </para>

    <para>The information in the table above was extracted from the Amazon
      documentation found at: <ulink
      url="http://ec2-downloads.s3.amazonaws.com/user_specified_kernels.pdf"/>.
      Kiwi images created for EC2 do not contain a partition table. Therefore,
      PVGrub images designated by <emphasis>h0</emphasis> in the manifest name
      need to be used with the images created by Kiwi.
    </para>

    <para>Kiwi can embed the appropriate PVGrub Kernel ID in the EC2
      manifest file if you specify the optional
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2region</sgmltag> as part of the
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2config</sgmltag> block in your
      <filename>config.xml</filename>. If you specify multiple regions Kiwi
      generates AMIs for each region specified. Supported values for the
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2region</sgmltag> element are
      <emphasis>AP-Singapore</emphasis>, <emphasis>EU-West</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>US-East</emphasis>, and <emphasis>US-West</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>With the appropriate boot kernel selected you can start your image.
      In this example we use the x86 Kernel in the US-East availability
      zone.
    </para>    

    <screen><command>ec2-run-instances</command> ami-... \
   --kernel aki-407d9529 \ 
   -k gsg-keypair </screen>

    <para>To check the state of your instance(s) use the
      command <command>ec2-describe-instances</command>.</para>

    <para>Once the instance state is shown as <emphasis 
        >running</emphasis> you can login into it using ssh as follows:
    </para>

    <screen><command>ssh</command> -i<!--
      --> <replaceable>PATH_TO_PRIVATE_KEY</replaceable> \
      root@<replaceable>YOUR_INSTANCE_ID</replaceable>
    </screen>

    <para>If you are unable to log in, it is most likely that the security
      setting for the instance is blocking the ssh access. To remedy this
      problem open port 22 using the <command>ec2-authorize</command>
      command as shown below.
    </para>

    <screen><command>ec2-authorize</command> default -p 22 </screen>

    <para>A few more remarks about EC2 are in order. As you have seen at the
     end of our example it is important that you include ssh in your image
     and that you start the ssh daemon in your image. Starting the sshd 
     process is accomplished by adding
     <emphasis>suseInsertService sshd</emphasis> in
     <filename>config.sh</filename>.
   </para>

   <para>Earlier in the example you generated a keypair that was then used
     to allow you to log into your running instance. The key does need to get
     injected into the instance when you launch it. This key injection happens
     through an init script <filename>/etc/init.d/amazon</filename>. This 
     script is provided by the <filename>suse-ami-tools</filename> package.
     Therefore, you need to include this package in the 
     <sgmltag class="element">packages</sgmltag> section of your
     <filename>config.xml</filename> file. You also need to make sure the
     <filename>amazon</filename> init script gets executed during boot by
     using <emphasis>suseInsertService amazon</emphasis> in your
     <filename>config.sh</filename> file.
   </para>

   <para>The key injection mechanism needs to access the network. Therefore,
     you must configure the network of your instance. The network interface 
     of the guest is always eth0 and it needs to be configured to use DHCP.
     See the overlay file tree of the example for configuration details.
   </para>

   <para>Last but not least some information about the storage options. Amazon
     offers S3 <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/"/> backed images
     (this is what we have worked with in this example) and EBS
     (Elastic Block Store) <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/ebs/"/> backed
     images. At the time of this writing it is not possible to use an image 
     format created by Kiwi with the Amazon tools directly to create an
     EBS backed image. It is possible to create an EBS volume from a KIWI
     raw image, but the process is cumbersome and requires a running Linux
     instance in EC2. It is anticipated that at some point in the future the
     Amazon team will address this problem and that the
     <command>ec2-import-instance</command> command in conjunction with the
     <command>ec2-upload-disk-image</command> command will be able to create
     EBS volumes from Linux based disk images. At this point you will be able
     to use the raw image created by KIWI to create an EBS backed image.
   </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
