<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.signkey">
  <title>Adding signing keys</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>package</primary>
    <secondary>rpm key</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>signing</primary>
    <secondary>build key</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>zypper</primary>
    <secondary>unknown package key</secondary>
  </indexterm>
   <para>
    The KIWI image build process uses the distribution package
    management system to install the specified packages into the unpacked
    image tree that forms the basis for the target image. Installation of
    these packages requires KIWI to import the GPG keys from the build
    system to the target system. This allows signature verification of the
    package signatures, but also implies that repositories used to build
    the image are also know on the build host. Using a repository for
    image building if that signing key is not in the build system key ring
    will break the image build. After the unpacked image tree is created
    and the package installation is complete the GPG keys are removed from
    from the key ring of the image root system.
   </para>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>rpm keys</primary>
    <secondary>importing</secondary>
  </indexterm>

   <para>In order to permanently import the package signing keys into
your appliance follow the steps outlined below:</para> 

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Add the package containing the build key to the packages section</para>
      <screen>&lt;package name="openSUSE-build-key">...&lt;/package></screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Call the import KIWI helper function in the config.sh script</para>
      <screen>suseImportBuildKey</screen>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>If the image is built with these settings KIWI installs the package containing the keys and imports them permanently to the rpm keyring.</para>

</chapter>
