<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.oem">
  <title>OEM Image—Preload Systems</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>OEM image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>images</primary>
    <secondary>OEM</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>OEM images</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>An OEM image is a virtual disk image representing all partitions
    and bootloader information in the same fashion it exists on a
    physical disk. The image format matches the format of the VMX image
    type. All flavors discussed previously for the VMX image type apply
    to the OEM image type. </para>


  <para>The basic idea behind an oem image is to provide the virtual
    disk data for OEM vendors to support easy deployment of the system
    to physical storage media. The deployment can be performed from any
    OS including Windows as long as a tool to dump data onto a disk
    device exists and is used. The oem image type may also be used to
    deploy an image on a USB stick. A USB stick is simply a removable
    physical storage device. </para>

    <sect1 id="sec.oem.building">
    <title>Building the suse-oem-preload Example</title>

    <para>
		The OEM example provided with kiwi is based on recent openSUSE
		releases, one example configuration per release, and includes the
		default and x11 patterns. The image type is a split type utilizing
		the distributions default filesystem format for the read-write
		partition and the <systemitem class="filesystem"
		>squashfs</systemitem> filesystem for the read-only partition.
		Using the additional <sgmltag class="attribute"
		>installiso</sgmltag> attribute creates an installable ISO
		image. When booting from the ISO image the OEM disk image will be
		deployed to the storage media on the booting machine (after
		confirmation by the user).
	</para>

<screen>
<command>cd</command> /usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/examples
==> select the example directory for the desired distribution change into it
<command>cd</command> suse-...
<command>kiwi</command> --build ./suse-oem-preload -d /tmp/myoem-result --type split
</screen>

    </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.oem.using">
    <title>Using the Image</title>
    <para>The virtual disk image created by KIWI with the commands shown
      above can be tested using virtualization software such as QEMU,
      VMware, or VirtualBox. The virtual disk is represented by the file
      with the <filename class="extension">.raw</filename> extension,
      whereas the file with the <filename class="extension"
        >.iso</filename> extension represents the installation disk for
      this oem image. The ISO image is bootable
        (<filename>filename.iso</filename>) and can be burned to optical
      media. It is recommended to test the image on a bare test system.
      The following command shows how to use QEMU to test the OEM disk
      image (<filename>filename.raw</filename>). </para>

<screen>
<command>cd</command> /tmp/myoem-result 
<command>qemu</command> suse-*-oem-preload.*.raw
</screen>

    <para>or using the <command>dd</command> command you can dump the
      image onto a test hard disk or USB stick and upon reboot select
      the appropriate device as the boot device in the BIOS: </para>

<screen>
<command>cd</command> /tmp/myoem-result 
<command>dd</command> if=suse-*-oem-preload.*.raw<!-- 
--> of=/dev/<replaceable>device</replaceable> bs=32k
</screen>

    <para>Note, when testing an oem image using the virtual disk image,
      i.e. the <filename class="extension">.raw</filename> file, the
      geometry of the disk image is not changed and therefore retains
      the disk geometry of the host system. This implies that the
      re-partitioning performed for a physical disk install during the
      oem boot workflow will be skipped. </para>

    <para>You can test the installation procedure in a virtual
      environment using the <filename class="extension">.iso</filename>
      file. In this case the re-partitioning code in the boot image will
      be executed. The following commands show this procedure using
      QEMU. </para>

<screen>
<command>cd</command> /tmp/myoem-result 
<command>qemu-img</command> create /tmp/mydisk 20G 
<command>qemu</command> -hda /tmp/mydisk<!-- 
--> -cdrom suse-*-oem-preload.*.iso -boot d
</screen>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.oem.flavours">
    <title>Flavours</title>
    <para>As indicated above the use of the <sgmltag class="attribute"
        >installiso</sgmltag> and <sgmltag class="attribute"
        >installstick</sgmltag> attributes for the oem image supports
      the creation of an installation image. The installation image can
      be created in two formats, one suitable for CD/DVD media and a
      second suitable for a USB stick. The self installing image deploys
      the oem image onto the selected storage device. The installation
      process is a simple image dump using the <command>dd</command> command.
      During this process the target system remains in terminal mode. The
      following configuration snippets show the use of the <sgmltag
        class="attribute">installiso</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
        class="attribute">installstick</sgmltag> attributes to create
      the ISO or USB installation image format respectively. </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <screen>&lt;type image="name" ... installiso="true"/&gt;</screen>
        <para>Creates a <filename class="extension">.iso</filename> file
          which can be burned onto a CD or a DVD. This represents an
          installation CD/DVD </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <screen>&lt;type image="name" ... installstick="true"/&gt;</screen>
        <para>Creates a <filename class="extension"
            >.raw.install</filename> file which can be dumped
            (<command>dd</command>) onto a USB stick. This represents an
          installation Stick </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="sec.oem.installation">
      <title>Specializing the OEM install process</title>
      <para>It is possible to specialize the OEM install process by providing
          shell scripts with the following names. For more information how
          to pack the scripts and make them work in the boot code, see
          the chapter <xref linkend="sec.hooks"/>.
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><filename>preHWdetect.sh</filename>
              This script is executed prior to the hardware scan on the
                  target machine.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><filename>preImageDump.sh</filename>
              This script is executed immediately prior to the OEM
                  image dump onto the target storage device.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><filename>postImageDump.sh</filename>
              This script is executed directly after the OEM image dump
                  onto the target storage device once the image checksum has
                  been successfully verified.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.oem.partitioning">
      <title>Influencing the OEM Partitioning</title>
      <para>By default the oemboot process will create/modify a swap,
          <filename>/home</filename> and <filename>/</filename>
        partition. It is possible to influence the behavior with the
          <sgmltag>oem-*</sgmltag> elements. See <xref
          linkend="chap.description"/> for details. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.oem.lvm">
      <title>LVM Support</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>LVM support</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>KIWI also provides support for LVM (Logical Volume
        Management). In this mode the disk partition table will include
        one lvm partition and one standard ext2 boot partition. KIWI
        creates the kiwiVG volume group, unless the lvmgroup attribute
        has been set, and adds logical volumes to the group based on the
        configuration given by the <sgmltag>systemdisk</sgmltag> block
        for this type. The filesystem for the volume group is determined
        by the <sgmltag class="attribute">filesystem</sgmltag> attribute
        of the type element. After booting the system the user has full
        control over the volume group and is free to change
        (resize/increase) the group and the volumes inside. Support for
        LVM has been added for all disk based image types. This includes
        the vmx and oem image types. In order to use LVM the existence
        of a <sgmltag class="element" >systemdisk</sgmltag> section is
        required. The <sgmltag class="element" >systemdisk</sgmltag>
        specification may be empty. An empty
        <sgmltag class="element" >systemdisk</sgmltag> specification triggers
        the creation of one LVM root volume with the default
        <emphasis>kiwiVG</emphasis> name.
      </para>

      <screen><command>kiwi</command> --create /tmp/myoem --type oem<!-- 
      --> -d /tmp/myoem-result --lvm</screen>

      <para>With the <sgmltag>systemdisk</sgmltag> section you
        can specify to have one or more top level directories in a
        separate volume. See <xref linkend="chap.description"/> for a
        detailed explanation. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.oem.partition-based-installation">
      <title>Partition Based Installation</title>
      <para>The default installation method of an OEM is dumping the
        entire virtual disk on the selected target disk and repartition
        the disk to the real geometry. This works but will also wipe
        everything which was on the disk before. KIWI also supports the
        installation into already existing partitions. This means the
        user can setup a disk with free partitions for the KIWI OEM
        installation process. This way already existing data will not be
        touched. In order to activate the partition based install mode
        the following oem option has to be set in
          <filename>config.xml</filename>: </para>

      <screen>&lt;oem-partition-install&gt;true&lt;/oem-partition-install&gt;</screen>

      <para>Compared to the disk based install the following differences
        should be mentioned: </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The bootloader will be setup to boot the installed
            system. There is no multiboot setup. The user is expected
            to implement the setup of a multiboot bootloader.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The oem options for system, swap and home doesn’t have
            any effect if the installation happens in predefined
            partitions. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>There is no support for remote (PXE) OEM installation
            because kiwi has to loop mount the disk image in order to
            access the partitions which can’t be done remotely. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The raw disk image is stored uncompressed on the install
            media. This is because KIWI needs to loop mount the disk
            image which it can’t do if the file is only available as
            compressed version. This means the install media in this
            mode will be approximately double the size of a standard
            install media. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="sec.oem.pxe-based-installation">
		<title>Network Based Installation</title>
		<para>
			Instead of manually dumping the OEM image on the target
			device or creating a kiwi install CD, USB stick, there is
			a third method of deploying the OEM image on the target
			device. It's possible to let the image be downloaded from
			a PXE boot server over the network. This requires a PXE
			network boot server to be setup properly in the first place
			For details how to do this refer to the
			chapter: <xref linkend="chap.pxe"/>. If your pxe server
			is running the following steps are required to setup
			the install process over the network
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Make sure you have created an install disk
					along with your oem image:
<screen>
&lt;type image="oem" ... installstick="true"/&gt;
</screen>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					loop mount the created .raw.install.raw file and copy the
					initrd and kernel images over to your pxe server
<screen>
kpartx -a install-image.raw.install.raw
mount /dev/mapper/loop0p1 /mnt
scp /mnt/boot/initrd.* pxe.server.ip:/srv/tftpboot/boot/initrd
scp /mnt/boot/linux.*  pxe.server.ip:/srv/tftpboot/boot/linux
umount /mnt
</screen>
				</para>
            </listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Compress the system image which lives inside the
					squashfs file. This is required because kiwi can't
					loop mount the squashfs over the network without
					a further export configuration. After the image has
					been gzip compressed the file is copied over to the
					pxe boot server
<screen>
mount /dev/mapper/loop0p2 /mnt || mount /dev/mapper/loop0p1 /mnt
mkdir /mnt2
mount -o loop /mnt/image-file.raw.squashfs /mnt2
gzip -c /mnt2/image-file.raw &gt; /tmp/image-file.gz
scp /tmp/image-file.gz   pxe.server.ip:/srv/tftpboot/image
scp /mnt2/image-file.md5 pxe.server.ip:/srv/tftpboot/image
umount /mnt2
rmdir  /mnt2
umount /mnt
</screen>
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					At last set the kernel commandline parameters
					via the append line in your PXE configuration
					(for example: pxelinux.cfg/default). It's important that
					at least the parameter <command>pxe=1</command> is added
					here.
				</para>
				<para>
					Additionally the boot parameters set in the bootloader
					configuration of the install disk has to be transfered
					over to the pxe boot configuration. It depends on the
					kiwi configuration which bootloader was used for the
					install disk, thus the configuration filename and format
					differs. For grub is's menu.lst for grub2 it's grub.cfg
					for uboot it would be boot.script. The example below
					assumes grub2 was used.
				</para>
				<para>
					Optionally the image can be stored on a FTP,HTTP server
					specified via the kiwiserver and kiwiservertype append
					information. In this case make sure you copied the
					system image and md5 file to the correct ftp,http
					location.
<screen>
mount /dev/mapper/loop0p1 /mnt
 ===> search bootloader setup e.g /mnt/boot/grub2/grub.cfg

 ===> copy loader=... and VGROUP=... information if present
      into the PXE configuration append line

vi pxelinux.cfg/default

LABEL ...
     kernel boot/linux
     append initrd=boot/initrd pxe=1 loader=... VGROUP=...

umount /mnt
</screen>
				</para>
            </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
