<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                                                 "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">


<chapter id="chap.instsourcesetup">
    <title>Installation Source</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>installation source</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Before you start to use any of the examples provided in the
        following chapters your build system has to have a valid
        installation source for the distribution you are about to create an
        image for. By default, all examples will connect to the network to
        find the installation source. It depends on your network bandwidth
        how fast an image creation process is and in almost all cases it is
        better to prepare a local installation source first. </para>

    <sect1 id="sec.instsourcesetup.adapt-example">
        <title>Adapt the Example’s config.xml</title>
        <para> If you can make sure you have a local installation source
            it’s important to change the path attribute inside of the
            repository element of the appropriate example to point to your
            local source directory. A typically default repository element
            looks like the following: </para>

        <screen>&lt;repository type="yast2"&gt;
     &lt;source path="opensuse://openSUSE:##.#/standard/"/&gt; 
     &lt;/repository&gt;</screen>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec.instsourcesetup.create-local-inst-source">
        <title>Create a Local Installation Source</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>KIWI</primary>
            <secondary>local installation source</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para> The following procedure describes how to create a local SUSE
            installation source which is stored below the path <filename
                class="directory">/images/CDs</filename>. If you are using the
            local path as described in this document you only need to flip
            the given path information inside of the example
                <filename>config.xml</filename> file. </para>

        <procedure id="proc.instsourcesetup.local-inst">
            <step>
                <para>Find your SUSE standard installation CDs or the DVD and
                    make them available to the build system. Most Linux systems
                    auto-mount a previously inserted media automatically. If this
                    is the case you simply can change the directory to the auto
                    mounted path below <filename class="directory"
                        >/media</filename>. If your system doesn’t mount the device
                    automatically you can do this with the following command: </para>
                <screen><command>mount</command> -o loop /dev/<replaceable>drive-device-name</replaceable> /mnt</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>If you do not have a DVD but a CD set, copy the contents
                    of <emphasis>all</emphasis> CDs into one directory. It’s
                    absolutely important that you first start with the
                        <emphasis>last</emphasis> CD and copy the first CD at last.
                    In case of CDs you should have a bundle of 4 CDs. Copy them in
                    the order 4 3 2 1. </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the contents of the CDs/DVD to your hard drive once
                    you have access to the media. You need at least 4GB free space
                    available. The following is intended to create an openSUSE
                    installation source: </para>

                <screen><command>mkdir</command> -p /image/CDs/full-##.#-i386/ 
<command>cp</command> -a /mnt/* /image/CDs/full-##.#-i386/ </screen>

                <para>Remember if you have a CD set start with number 4 first
                    and after that, eject the CD and insert the next one to
                    repeat the copy command until all CDs are copied into to
                    /image </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
