<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.installation">
  <title>Installation</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>Installation</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect1 id="sec.installation.rpminstall">
    <title>Installing using Packages</title>
    <para>Once you have added the appropriate repositories (more on
      this below) to your system you can search for the kiwi packages through
      the YaST interface or using <command>zypper</command> as shown
      below.</para>
      
    <screen><command>zypper</command> se kiwi</screen>

    <para>The list of packages returned by zypper contains the main package,
      simply named <filename>kiwi-</filename>, the
      <filename>-doc</filename> package containing the documentation files,
      and  the <filename>-desc-</filename> packages containing the boot
      descriptions for the various image types. Installing this set of
      packages is sufficient to build your images.</para>

    <para>Adding repositories to your system can be accomplished using the
      YaST interface or the <command>zypper ar</command> command.</para>
      
    <sect2 id="sec.installation.reops">
      <title>Package Repositories</title>
      <para>The simplest and most straight forward way to install KIWI is
        to use the packages that are provided in the Virtualization:Appliances
        project on the web here: <filename>http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Virtualization:/Appliances/</filename></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.installation.fromsource">
    <title>Running from Source</title>
    <para>KIWI is developed and maintained in a git repository on GitHub.
      You can clone the source code using the following command.</para>

    <screen><command>git</command> clone <!--
       -->https://github.com/openSUSE/kiwi.git</screen>

    <para>Before running from source you want to verify that all the
      dependencies are satisfied. The best way to accomplish this is to
      install all packages listed as <emphasis>BuildRequires</emphasis>
      in the <filename>.spec</filename> file found in the
      <filename>rpm</filename> directory. Once all dependent packages are
      installed change your working directory to the
      <filename>kiwi</filename> directory and run kiwi as follows:
      </para>

    <screen><command>./kiwi</command></screen>

    <para>The KIWI self tests are executed using:</para>

    <screen><command>make</command> test</screen>

    <para>If you want to refresh your source with the latest checked in code
      you can simply pull the latest sources from the GitHub repository
      using the command shown below.</para>

    <screen><command>git</command> pull</screen>

  </sect1>
</chapter>
