<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.raid">
  <title>KIWI RAID Support</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>RAID</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
   KIWI supports three types of RAID systems:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Real RAID controllers with its own firmware</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         KIWI only has to make sure the drivers are part of the
         initrd e.g cciss for the smart array controllers built
         into some server boards.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>BIOS RAID controllers</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         Cheap onboard controller devices with the RAID
         software inside the BIOS (so called fake RAID).
         Linux supports some of them with the 'dmraid' utility
         and the support is a mix of BIOS calls and some
         device mapper calls.
        </para>
        <para>
         The check for these devices can be switched on
         and off with &lt;oem-ataraid-scan&gt;true|false&lt;/oem-ataraid-scan&gt;
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Linux software RAID</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         There is no hardware involved. The Linux kernel
         can control any storage device by adding RAID
         capabilities. All the work done by a real hardware
         controller is done in software. 
        </para>
        <para>
         All this is done using the 'mdadm' utility.
         The metadata for the devices are stored in RAID
         blocks on the storage device which requires them
         to be of the correct partition type.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   The software RAID is supported in a so called degraded mode.
   This means the RAID is created but not all devices to build
   it are attached. That's because an image consists initially
   out of one disk and not more. The user should add devices or
   change the RAID mode manually after deployment. This is an
   easy task if the system comes up prepared for all this. In
   order to use linux software raid in kiwi images you only have
   to set:
  </para>
  <para>
   &lt;type ... mdraid="mirroring"&gt;
  </para>
  <para>
   Currently kiwi supports a degraded mirroring (raid:1) or
   stripping (raid:0) config
   but you can change the mode to any supported raid level after
   deployment.
  </para>
</chapter>

