<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.iso">
  <title>ISO Image / Live System</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>ISO image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>images</primary>
    <secondary>ISO</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>ISO images</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>A live system image is an operating System on CD or DVD. In
    principle one can treat the CD/DVD as the hard disk of the system
    with the restriction that you can’t write data on it. So as soon as
    the media is plugged into the computer, the machine is able to boot
    from that media. After some time one can login to the system and
    work with it like on any other system. By default All write actions
    takes place in RAM space and therefore all changes will be lost
    as soon as the computer shuts down.</para>

  <sect1 id="sec.iso.building">
    <title>Building a live JeOS</title>

    <para>This example is based on SLES version 12.</para>

<screen><command>kiwi</command> --build suse-SLE12-JeOS -d /tmp/myiso-result --type iso</screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.iso.using">
    <title>Using the Image</title>
    <para>There are two ways to use the generated ISO image: </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Burn the <filename class="extension">.iso</filename> file
          on a CD or DVD with your preferred burn program. Plug in the
          CD or DVD into a test computer and (re)boot the machine. Make
          sure the computer boot from the CD drive as first boot device.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use a virtualization system to test the image directly.
          Testing an iso can be done with any full virtual system for
          example:</para>
<screen><command>qemu</command> -cdrom /tmp/myiso-result/LimeJeOS-SLE12.x86_64-1.13.1.iso</screen>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.iso.flavours">
    <title>Flavours</title>
    <para>
    KIWI supports different filesystems and boot methods along
    with the ISO image type. The provided example by default uses an
    <systemitem class="filesystem">overlayfs</systemitem> based compressed
    root filesystem. overlayfs allows to combine two filesystems into
    one. The root filesystem exists as compressed squashfs filesystem
    and all write operations are redirected in RAM or in a persistent
    area on a disk. The result is a full writable live-system.

    The flags attribute in <filename>config.xml</filename> exists to be
    able to have the following alternative solutions:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><sgmltag class="attribute">flags</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
            class="attvalue">compressed</sgmltag>"</term>
        <listitem>
          <para> Does filesystem compression with squashfs, but don’t
            use an overlay filesystem for write support. A symbolic link
            list is used instead and thus a split element is required in
            <filename>config.xml</filename>. See the split mode
            section below for details. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><sgmltag class="attribute">flags</sgmltag>="<sgmltag
            class="attvalue">seed</sgmltag>"</term>
        <listitem>
          <para> Creates a <systemitem class="filesystem"
              >btrfs</systemitem> image and allows write operations
            into a cow (seed) file. In case of an ISO the seed device is created
            on a ramdisk.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Flags Not Set</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If no <sgmltag class="attribute">flags</sgmltag>
            attribute is set no compressed filesystem, no overlay
            filesystem will be used. The root tree will be directly part
            of the ISO filesystem and the paths:
              <filename>/bin</filename>, <filename>/boot</filename>,
              <filename>/lib</filename>, <filename>/lib64</filename>,
              <filename>/opt</filename>, <filename>/sbin</filename>, and
              <filename>/usr</filename> will be read-only. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <sect2 id="sec.iso.split-mode">
      <title>Split mode</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>split mode</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>overlay filesystem</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>If no overlay filesystem is in use but the image filesystem
        is based on a compressed filesystem KIWI allows to setup which
        files and directories should be writable in a so called split
        section. In order to allow to login into the system, at least
        the <filename class="directory">/var</filename> directory should
        be writable. This is because the PAM authentication requires
        to be able to report any login attempt to
          <filename>/var/log/messages</filename> which therefore needs
        to be writable. The following split section can be used if the
        flag compressed is used: </para>

<screen>&lt;split&gt; 
  &lt;persistent&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/var"/&gt;
     &lt;file name="/var/*"/&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/boot"/&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/boot/*"/&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/etc"/&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/etc/*"/&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/home"/&gt; 
     &lt;file name="/home/*"/&gt;
     &lt;file name="/tmp"/&gt;
     &lt;file name="/tmp/*"/&gt;
  &lt;/persistent&gt; 
&lt;/split&gt;</screen>

    </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.iso.hybrid-mode">
    <title>Hybrid mode</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>KIWI</primary>
      <secondary>hybrid mode</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>KIWI</primary>
      <secondary>USB sticks</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      A hybrid image is a iso image including a partition table and can
      therefore be attached as a CD/DVD <emphasis>and</emphasis> as a
      normal disk to the system. This has the advantage that a hybrid
      iso live system can be burned to a CD/DVD as well as uploaded to
      a USB stick. In order to activate the hybrid feature the hybrid
      flag must be set to true as indicated below. 
    </para>

<screen>&lt;type image="iso" ... hybrid="true"/&gt;</screen>    
  </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
  <title>USB stick images</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>USB</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    kiwi supports two types of USB stick images. The first type which
    are the hybrid ISO images and basically the same as the live ISO images
    and the second type which are the OEM virtual disk images.
    The deployment of both types can be performed from any OS including
    Windows as long as a tool to dump data onto a disk device exists
    and is used.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>ISO Hybrid stick</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>KIWI</primary>
      <secondary>Hybrid stick</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      As indicated above a hybrid iso image also works as USB stick image.
      If a hybrid iso is used like a disk image on a writable medium
      like a USB stick it's possible to write into a persistent area on
      the stick instead of the RAM. kiwi will create an additional ext2
      partition to store that information on the disk if the attribute
      hybridpersistent is set to true.
    </para>

<screen>&lt;type image="iso" ... hybridpersistent="true"/&gt;</screen>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>OEM USB stick</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>KIWI</primary>
      <secondary>OEM stick</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para> In contrast to the hybrid iso image it's also possible to
        create a oem virtual disk image which is dumped on the stick.
        The big advantage with this approach is, that it's possible to
        create a stick which contains a live OS but also a data
        partition for custom data. The data partition is a fat partition
        also recognized by the Windows operating system. In order to
        create such a Windows friendly stick one has to pass the option
          <option>--fat-storage &lt;size-in-MB&gt;</option>.
        <screen><command>kiwi</command> --create ... --fat-storage 500</screen>
        If this option is set kiwi will use the syslinux bootloader for
        the image as well as the first partition as fat partition of the
        specified size. The live OS itself will live in a LVM which
        allows easy manipulation of the logical root volume. For further
        information about the OEM image type please refer to the OEM
        chapter <xref linkend="chap.oem"/>
      </para>
    <sect3>
      <title>OEM compressed / readonly USB stick</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>compressed root</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    <para> If a compressed filesystem type like overlayfs is used for the
          image root directory it's also possible to allow persistent
          writing on the USB stick or alternatively disallow that and
          let all write actions perfom in RAM only. kiwi provides the
          type attribute ramonly for this purpose. So in order to create
          a read-only oem stick with compressed root filesystem the
          following type section is required:
          <screen>&lt;type image="oem" filesystem="overlayfs" ramonly="true"/&gt;</screen>
        </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
