<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                                                 "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.vmx">
    <title>VMX Image—Virtual Disks</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>VMX image</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>images</primary>
        <secondary>VMX</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>VMX images</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>A VMX image is a virtual disk image for use in full
        virtualization systems like Qemu or VMware. The image is a file
        containing the system represented by the configured packages in
        <filename>config.xml</filename> as well as partition data and bootloader
        information. The size of this virtual disk can be specified by using the size element
        in the <filename>config.xml</filename> file or by adding the
            <option>--bootvm-disksize</option> command line argument. </para>
    
    <sect1 id="sec.vmx.building">
        <title>Building the suse-vm-guest Example</title>
        <para> The vm-guest example provided with KIWI is based on recent
            openSUSE releases, one example configuration per release. The
            example uses base pattern and the virtual disk is formatted using
            the distribution default filesystem. </para>

        <screen><command>cd</command> /usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/examples 
<command>cd</command> suse-...
<command>kiwi</command> --prepare ./suse-vm-guest --root /tmp/myvm </screen>

        <screen><command>kiwi</command> --create /tmp/myvm --type vmx -d /tmp/myvm-result</screen>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec.vmx.using">
        <title>Using the Image</title>
        <para>The generated virtual disk image serves as the hard disk of
            the selected virtualization system (QEMU, VMware, etc.). The
            virtual hard disk format differs across virtualization
            environments. Some virtualization environments support multiple
            virtual disk formats. Using the QEMU virtualization environment
            test the created image with the following command: </para>

        <screen><command>cd</command> /tmp/myvm-result 
<command>qemu</command> suse-##.#-vm-guest.i686-1.1.2.raw -m 256 </screen>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="sec.vmx.flavours">
        <title>Flavours</title>
        <para>KIWI always generates a file in the <filename
                class="extension">.raw</filename> format. The .raw file is a
            disk image with a structure equivalent to the structure of a
            physical hard disk. Individual virtualization systems have
            specific formats to facilitate improved I/O performance to the
            virtual disk, represented by the image file, or additional
            specified virtual hard disk files. KIWI will generate a specific
            format when the format attribute of the type element is added. </para>

        <screen>&lt;type image="vmx"... format="name"/&gt;</screen>

        <para>The following table lists the supported virtual disk
            formats:</para>

        <table id="tab.vmx.supported-disk-formats">
            <title>Supported Virtual Disk Formats</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>KIWI</primary>
                <secondary>virtual disk formats</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>virtual disk formats</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Name</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>vmdk</entry>
                        <entry>Disk format for VMware</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>vhd</entry>
                        <entry>Disk format for Microsoft HyperV</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>ovf</entry>
                        <entry>Open Virtual Format requires VMware's ovftool</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>qcow2</entry>
                        <entry>QEMU virtual disk format</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>      
        </table>

        <sect2 id="sec.vmx.vmware-support">
            <title>VMware support</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>KIWI</primary>
                <secondary>VMware</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>VMware</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>A VMware image is accompanied by a guest configuration file.
                This file includes information about the hardware to be
                represented to the guest image by the VMware virtualization
                environment as well as specification of resources such as
                memory. </para>

            <para>Within the <filename>config.xml</filename> file it is
                possible to specify the VMware configuration settings. In
                addition it is possible to include selected packages in the
                created image that are specific to the VM image generation. The
                following <filename>config.xml</filename> snippet provides
                general guidance on the elements in
                    <filename>config.xml</filename>. </para>

            <screen>&lt;packages type="vmx"&gt; 
     <sgmltag class="sgmlcomment"> packages you need in VMware only </sgmltag>
&lt;/packages&gt; 
&lt;type......&gt;
    &lt;machine memory="512"&gt; 
        &lt;vmdisk controller="ide" id="0"/&gt; 
    &lt;/machine&gt; 
&lt;/type&gt;</screen>

            <para>Given the specification above KIWI will create a VMware
                guest configuration specifying the availability of 512&nbsp;MB
                of RAM and an IDE disk controller interface for the VM guest.
                For additional information about the configuration settings
                please refer to the <emphasis>machine</emphasis> section. </para>

            <para>The guest configuration can be loaded through VMware user
                interface and may be modified through the GUI. The configuration
                file has the <filename class="extension">.vmx</filename>
                extension as shown in the example below. </para>

            <screen>/tmp/myvm-result/suse-##.#-vm-guest.i686-1.1.2.vmx</screen>

            <para>Using the <sgmltag class="attribute"
                    >format</sgmltag>="<sgmltag class="attvalue">vmdk</sgmltag>"
                attribute of the <sgmltag class="starttag">type</sgmltag> start
                tag will create the VMware formatted disk image (<filename
                    class="extension">.vmdk</filename> file) and the required
                VMware guest configuration (<filename class="extension"
                    >.vmx</filename>) file. </para>

            <para>In addition it is possible to create an image for the Xen
                virtualization framework. By adding the <sgmltag
                    class="attribute">bootprofile</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
                    class="attribute">bootkernel</sgmltag> attributes to the
                    <sgmltag class="starttag">type</sgmltag> start tag with values
                of <sgmltag class="attvalue">xen</sgmltag> and <sgmltag
                    class="attvalue">xenboot</sgmltag>, respectively. Please refer
                to the <xref linkend="chap.xen"/> for additional details.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="sec.vmx.lvm">
            <title>LVM Support</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>KIWI</primary>
                <secondary>LVM support</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>KIWI also provides support for LVM (Logical Volume
                Management). In this mode the disk partition table will include
                one lvm partition and one standard <systemitem
                    class="filesystem">ext2</systemitem> boot partition. KIWI
                creates the kiwiVG volume group and adds logical volumes as they
                are needed and configured according to the image type and
                filesystem. After boot of the system the user has full control
                over the volume group and is free to change/resize/increase the
                group and the volumes inside. Support for LVM has been added for
                all image types which are disk based. This includes vmx, oem and
                usb. In order to use LVM for the vmx type just add the
                    <option>--lvm</option> option as part of the KIWI create step
                or add the attribute lvm="true" as part of the type section in
                your <filename>config.xml</filename> file. </para>

            <screen><command>kiwi</command> --create /tmp/myvm --type vmx<!--
             --> -d /tmp/myvm-result --lvm </screen>

            <para>With the optional systemdisk section you can set one or more
                top level directories into a separate volume. See <xref
                    linkend="chap.description"/> for a detailed explanation.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
