<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.ec2">
  <title>EC2 Image—Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>KIWI</primary>
    <secondary>EC2 image</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>images</primary>
    <secondary>EC2</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud</primary>
    <see>EC2 image</see>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>EC2 images</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>The <trademark>Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud</trademark> (Amazon
    EC2) provides an environment known as 
    <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IAAS">
      <citetitle>IAAS</citetitle></ulink> (Infrastrcuture as a Service).
    In this environment you have the ability to run Virtual
    Machines (VMs) on hardware managed by Amazon and the virtualization
    infrastructure provided by Amazon.</para>

  <para>The virtualization infrastructure for EC2 is setup to work with
    Amazon Machine Images (AMIs). There are two storage models for AMIs:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/">
             <citetitle>S3</citetitle></ulink> (Simple Storage Service)
          backed AMI
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara>
          <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/ebs/">
            <citetitle>EBS</citetitle></ulink> (Elastic Block Store)
          backed AMI 
        </simpara>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    The image created with KIWI can be used to create an AMI for both
    storage models. For an S3 backed AMI a bundle with a manifest XML file
    is required and KIWI uses the Amazon tools to create this bundle for you.
    With the bundle created all you have to do is upload the bundle using
    the EC2 tools, register a new AMI and run the registered AMI.</para>

  <para>For an EBS backed AMI the procedure to get to a working AMI requires
    more manual steps when compared to the S3 backed AMI approach. KIWI does
    not provide any automation for this process at this time. The KIWI
    created image needs to be uploaded to EC2 and then it needs to be dumped
    to an EBS volume. This implies that you need to have a running AMI in
    EC2</para>

  <para>The procedures to handle both storage options are outlined
    below.</para>

  <para>You can work with EC2 using the Amazon Web application found
    at <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com"/> or you can use the Amazon
    provided command line tools. In this example we will exclusively
    interact with EC2 using the command line tools. The command line tools
    are devided into <emphasis>AMI</emphasis> and <emphasis>API</emphasis>
    tools. The AMI tools are designed to operate on images, while
    the API tools are designed to work with the Amazon <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer">
      <citetitle>REST API</citetitle></ulink>. In order for KIWI to create
    the bundle for S3 backed AMIs the Amazon AMI tools must be installed.
    It is recommended that you install both, the AMI and API tools on your
    build system.</para>

  <para>The Amazon tools are not distributed with KIWI and can be
    installed using packages from the openSUSE Build Service <ulink
      url="http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Virtualization:/Cloud:/EC2/"><citetitle>Virtualization:Cloud:EC2</citetitle></ulink> repository,
    or can be downloaded from Amazon at 
    <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/developertools/368"/> and
    <ulink url="http://aws.amazon.com/developertools/351"/>.</para>

  <para>Documentation for Amazon EC2 can be found at <ulink
        url="http://aws.amazon.com/documentation/ec2/"/>. The documentation
    for the command line tools may be accessed at <ulink url="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AWSEC2/latest/CommandLineReference"/>. All commands also
    support the customary <option>--help</option> command line option to
    display the supported command line arguments for the given command.</para>

  <para>When working with the Amazon tools it is useful to set the
    EC2_HOME, EC2_PRIVATE_KEY, and EC2_CERT environment variables. Setting
    EC2_PRIVATE_KEY, and EC2_CERT allows you to forego specification of the
    <option>--private-key</option> and <option>--cert</option> command line
    options with every command. The EC2_HOME environment variable is used by
    the tools to find required libraries.
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>EC2_HOME</para>
        <para>Location of the bin and lib directories installed by the
            Amazon tools. A good location for the tools on your
            system is <filename>/usr/local</filename>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>EC2_PRIVATE_KEY</para>
        <para>Path to your private key file (including the filename). For
            example <filename>/home/USERNAME/AWS/keys/pk-....pem</filename>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>EC2_CERT</para>
        <para>Path to your certificate file (including the filename). For
            example <filename>/home/USERNAME/AWS/keys/cert-....pem</filename>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>Please note that your account will be billed by Amazon at the 
   published rate for any computing resources you consume in EC2. This
   includes but is not limited to, running instances, storing data
   (your image) on S3 or EBS, and network traffic.</para>

  <para>One final remark before we get started, the default region for any
    <command>ec2-</command> command that communicates with the REST API or
    sends files to EC2 is the US-East region, i.e. us-east-1. Therefore, if
    you want to upload any data to other EC2 regions you must specify the
    desired target region. Specifying a region is accomplished by setting
    the EC2_URL environment variable, by using the <option>--url</option>
    command line option, or by using the <option>--region</option> argument.
    The EC2-URL environment variable and the <option>--url</option> argument
    expect a value in the form
    <replaceable>https://ec2.amazonaws.com</replaceable> (us-east-1).
    The <option>--region</option> argument expects the name of
    a region as returned by the <command>ec2-describe-regions</command>
    command. The region specified for the <command>ec2-</command> commands
    must match the specified in the <filename>config.xml</filename> if this
    option was specified in your configuration.
  </para>
    
  <sect1 id="sec.ec2.building">
    <title>Building the suse-ec2-guest Example</title>
    <para>The example provided with KIWI uses openSUSE as the base
      distribution and includes the base pattern plus the vim editor. Also
      included is the suse-ami-tools package that provides tools needed
      in the EC2 environment.
    </para>
    <para>Prior to building the EC2 example verify that the EC2 command line
      tools are installed and work as expected by executing the

      <screen><command>ec2-describe-images</command> -a</screen>

      command. The result is a list of all available images in EC2 printed to
      your terminal. Additionaly you need to edit the
      <filename>config.xml</filename> file of the example and enter your EC2
      account information. Replace the values for
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2accountnr</sgmltag>,
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2privatekeyfile</sgmltag>, and
      <sgmltag class="element">ec2certfile</sgmltag>. Note that the account
      number is displayed with dashes ("-") on the Amazon web site, but the
      entry in <filename>config.xml</filename> is expected to be numeric only.
      The private key file is the private file you downloaded when you
      created your certificate. It is recommended to create a copy of the
      example <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/kiwi/examples/suse-<replaceable>Version</replaceable>/suse-ec2-guest</filename>.</para>

    <para>You are now ready to build the EC2 example. Lets assume you copied
      the example configuration directory to
      <filename class="directory">/tmp</filename> prior to modifying the
      <filename>config.xml</filename> file.</para>
 
      <screen><command>kiwi</command> --prepare <!--
        -->/tmp/suse-ec2-guest --root /tmp/myec2</screen>

      <screen><command>kiwi</command> --create <!--
        -->/tmp/myec2 -d /tmp/myec2-result -y</screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.ec2.using">
    <title>Using EC2 and the created image</title>
    <para>Upon completion of the image build all files necessary for an S3
      backed AMI and for an EBS backed AMI can be found in your destination
      directory, <filename class="directory">/tmp/myec2-result</filename> if
      you followed the commands given above. Prior to describing the specifics
      about using the KIWI produced images the following section will address
      some rudimentary general EC2 concepts and commands that can be used with
      existing AMIs and the AMIs you can register with the KIWI created
      images.</para>

    <sect2 id="sec.ec2.using.general">
      <title>Using a registered AMI</title>
      <para>This section is not a replacement for the EC2 documention
        mentioned earlier. We will only cover the concepts and commands
        necessary to get you started such that you can launch the KIWI
        created image in this example.</para>

      <para>Prior to launching any instance in EC2 you need to have a keypair.
        If you do not already have a keypair in EC2 you can create one using
        the <command>ec2-add-keypair</command> command. This creates a
        public/private keypair that is used to grant you access to your 
        running instance via the ssh tools. Generate the keypair as shown
        below, the <replaceable>gsgkey</replaceable> name is arbitrary
        and used in this example, you can choose any name you like. The use
        of the key is quite frequent. Therefore, you probably want to choose
        a name that is easy to remember and not too terribly long to
        type.</para>
  
      <screen><command>ec2-add-keypair</command> <!--
        --><replaceable>gsgkey</replaceable> </screen>
  
      <para>Save the private key returned by the command in a local file.
        Using your favorite text editor, paste everything between
        (and including) the <literal>-----BEGIN RSA PRIVATE KEY-----</literal>
        and <literal>-----END RSA PRIVATE KEY-----</literal> lines into your
        editor and save the key to a file. The file can have any name. However,
        it makes sense to name the file after the keypair name you have
        chosen earlier. If the file is named differently from the keypair
        you will end up launching instances with <option>-k</option>
        <replaceable>mykey</replaceable> and then accessing the instance
        with <option>-i</option> <replaceable>yourkey</replaceable>, which
        may be a bit weird. As indicated by the heading, this is your
        private key, thus make sure you safe guard it appropriately. On Linux
        the ssh tools will complain if the key file does not have the proper
        permissions. Change the permissions of your private key file to be
        read-write by you, the owner, only.

        <screen><command>chown</command> 600 <!--
          --><replaceable>gsgkey</replaceable> </screen>

        The public key of your keypair is stored in the EC2 infrastructure.
        EC2 allows you to have multiple keypairs, to review your existing
        keypairs use the <command>ec2-describe-keypairs</command> command.
      </para>
  
      <para>When you launch an instance of an AMI you must specify a keypair
        name. This selects the public key to be injected into the instance.
        The key injection occurs through the <filename>amazon</filename>
        init script provided by the <filename>suse-ami-tools</filename>
        package. This package, as mentioned previously, is already included
        in the example's <filename>config.xml</filename> file. Do not forget
        to include this package when you create your own image descriptions
        for EC2 or you will not be able to log into your running instances.
        Additionally you need to activate this service by adding
        <emphasis>suseInsertService amazon</emphasis> in your
        <filename>config.sh</filename> file.</para>
  
      <para>The key injection mechanism needs to access the network. Therefore,
        you must configure the network when you build your image.
        Configuration of the network can be accomplished through the overlay
        mechanism or via commands in config.sh. The network interface of a
        guest in EC2 is always eth0 and it needs to be configured to use DHCP.
        In the example the overlay mechanism is used to setup the network
        configuration.</para>

      <para>Another prerequisite to launching an instance in EC2 is knowing
        the AMI you want to instantiate. As you have already seen, the
        <command>ec2-describe-images</command> command with the
        <option>-a</option> option will provide information about all publicly
        available AMIs. Using the command without the <option>-a</option>
        option will provide information about your registered images.</para>

      <para>The Amazon EC2 infrastructure uses <ulink
        url="http://www.linode.com/wiki/index.php/PV-GRUB">
        <citetitle>PVGrub (Para-Virtual Grub)</citetitle></ulink> to
        boot instances of an AMI. This allows instances to run the kernel
        that is part of the AMI, rather than some kernel provided by the
        Amazon infrastructure. However, an Amazon provided kernel is still
        required to kick things off and in the startup process PVGrub
        eventually picks up the <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename> file
        in your image and then boots the kernel specified. Note, that during
        the boot process you do not have access to a console and thus it makes
        no sense to have multiple kernel entries in your
        <filename>menu.lst</filename> file. Without console access you do not
        have an opportunity to choose a kernel. Each EC2 region has it's own
        independent copy of this boot mechanism and the boot mechanism is
        differentiated between 32 bit and 64 bit. The boot kernels are named
        with an ID that starts with the TLA (Three Letter Acronym)
        <emphasis>aki</emphasis> followed by a dash ("-") and a hex number.
        The <xref linkend="tab.ec2.kernel-image-ids" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
        table below provides guidelines for the selection of the boot kernel
        ID based on Region and image architecture.</para>
  
        <table id="tab.ec2.kernel-image-ids">
          <title>Amazon Kernel Image IDs</title>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="4*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Region</entry>
                <entry>AKI</entry>
                <entry>Arch</entry>
                <entry>Name</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>AP-Northeast</entry>
                <entry>aki-ec5df7ed</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-ap-northeast-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-i386.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>AP-Northeast</entry>
                <entry>aki-ee5df7ef</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-ap-northeast-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>AP-Southeast</entry>
                <entry>aki-a4225af6</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-ap-southeast-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-i386.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>AP-Southeast</entry>
                <entry>aki-aa225af8</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-ap-southeast-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>EU-West</entry>
                <entry>aki-64695810</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-eu/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-i386.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>EU-West</entry>
                <entry>aki-62695816</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-eu/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>SA-East</entry>
                <entry>aki-bc3ce3a1</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-sa/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-i386.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>SA-East</entry>
                <entry>aki-cc3ce3d1</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-sa/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>US-East</entry>
                <entry>aki-805ea7e9</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-i386.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>US-East</entry>
                <entry>aki-825ea7eb</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>US-West</entry>
                <entry>aki-83396bc6</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-us-west-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>US-West</entry>
                <entry>aki-8d396bc8</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-us-west-1/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>US-West2</entry>
                <entry>aki-c2e26ff2</entry>
                <entry>x86</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-us-west-2/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>US-West2</entry>
                <entry>aki-98e26fa8</entry>
                <entry>x86-64</entry>
                <entry><filename>ec2-public-images-us-west-2/pv-grub-hd0-V1.02-x86_64.gz.manifest.xml</filename></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
    
      <para>The information in the table above was extracted from the Amazon
        documentation found at: <ulink
        url="http://ec2-downloads.s3.amazonaws.com/user_specified_kernels.pdf"/>.
        </para>

        <para>KIWI images created for EC2 do not contain a partition table.
        Therefore, PVGrub images designated by <emphasis>h0</emphasis> in the
        manifest name need to be used with the images created by Kiwi.</para>
  
      <para>Specifying the optional
        <sgmltag class="element">ec2region</sgmltag> element as part of the
        <sgmltag class="element">ec2config</sgmltag> block in your
        <filename>config.xml</filename> file instructs KIWI to embed the
        appropriate PVGrub Kernel ID in the EC2 manifest file of the bundle.
        Therefore, you can create region specific bundles. KIWI will create
        a bundle for each specified region. Supported values
        for the <sgmltag class="element">ec2region</sgmltag> element are
        <emphasis>AP-Northeast</emphasis>, <emphasis>AP-Southeast</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>EU-West</emphasis>, <emphasis>US-East</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>US-West</emphasis>, and <emphasis>US-West2</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Public images in EC2 already have the boot kernel information
        embedded. If you build a generic image with EC2 by not specifying
        the EC2 region you will need to specify the appropriate boot kernel
        on the command line when you launch an instance of your AMI as shown
        below. The example uses the x86 Kernel in the US-East region.</para>
  
      <screen><command>ec2-run-instances</command> ami-... <!--
        -->--kernel aki-407d9529 -k gsgkey </screen>
  
      <para>To check the state of your instance(s) use the
        command <command>ec2-describe-instances</command>.</para>
  
      <para>Once the instance state for an instance is shown as
        <emphasis>running</emphasis> you can log into the instance using
        ssh as follows:</para>
  
      <screen><command>ssh</command> -i<!--
        --> <replaceable>PATH_TO_PRIVATE_KEY</replaceable> <!--
        -->root@<replaceable>PUBLIC_IP_OF_YOUR_INSTANCE</replaceable></screen>
  
      <para>The <replaceable>PUBLIC_IP_OF_YOUR_INSTANCE</replaceable> is
        displayed as part of the output of the
        <command>ec2-describe-instances</command> command. If you are unable
        to log in, it is most likely that the security
        setting for the instance is blocking the ssh access, or that you did
        not enable the ssh daemon process on startup. Your
        <filename>config.sh</filename> script should have a line activating
        the ssh daemon as follows,
        <emphasis>suseInsertService sshd</emphasis>. If you do not have this
        entry in <filename>config.sh</filename> you will have to rebuild your
        image. Addressing the problem with port blocking is acomplished using
        the <command>ec2-authorize</command> command to open port 22 as shown
        below.</para>
  
      <screen><command>ec2-authorize</command> default -p 22 </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.ec2.using.S3">
      <title>Using the bundle for an S3 backed AMI</title>
      <para>The destination directory,
        <filename class="directory">/tmp/myec2-result</filename> if you
        followed the commands given above contains a directory ending
        with <filename class="directory">-any</filename>. This directory
        contains the AMI bundle created by KIWI with the Amazon tools for use
        with the S3 storage model. The 
        <filename class="directory">-any</filename> ending of the directory
        name indicates that this bundle may be deployed to any EC2 region.
        As described earlier you can use the
        <sgmltag class="element">ec2region</sgmltag> element in
        <filename>config.xml</filename> to build bundles for specific EC2
        regions. If the <sgmltag class="element">ec2region</sgmltag> element
        is used the directory name containing the bundle will end with the
        appropriate region string.</para>

      <para>The generated bundle needs to be transfered to Amazon using the
        <command>ec2-upload-bundle</command> command line tool. This tool is
        part of the Amazon API tools. Upload the AMI as follows, replacing 
        <replaceable>AWS_Key_ID</replaceable> and
        <replaceable>AWS_secret_Key_ID</replaceable> with your Amazon key
        information. Also you may want to choose a different name for your
        bucket than <filename>myImages</filename>. If the bucket does not
        exist in S3 it will be created.</para>
    
      <!-- formating is ugly here but looks reasonably good in the html-->
      <screen><command>ec2-upload-bundle</command> <!--
        --> -b <replaceable>myImages</replaceable> <!--
        --> -a <replaceable>AWS_Key_ID</replaceable> <!--
        --> -s <replaceable>AWS_secret_Key_ID</replaceable> \
   -m /tmp/myec2/suse-##.#-ec2-guest.<replaceable>ARCH</replaceable>-<!--
        --><replaceable>Version</replaceable>.ec2-any/ \
      suse-##.#-ec2-guest.<replaceable>ARCH</replaceable>-<!--
        --><replaceable>Version</replaceable>.ami.manifest.xml</screen>

      <para>Where <replaceable>ARCH</replaceable> indicates the architecture
        to be used for this image, 32 bit (i686) or 64 bit (x86_64), and
        <replaceable>Version</replaceable> matches the value of the
        <sgmltag class="element">version</sgmltag> element in the
        <filename>config.xml</filename> file.</para>

      <para>After the upload process is complete, register your image with the
        EC2 infrastructure using the <command>ec2-register</command>
        command as shown below. The result of the registration
        process is an AMI ID returned on the command line in the form
        <quote>ami-</quote> followed by a random key sequence. Use this
        AMI ID to launch your instance as described in the
        <xref  linkend="sec.ec2.using.general" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
        section.</para>

      <screen><command>ec2-register</command> myImages/<!--
        -->suse-##.#-ec2-guest.<replaceable>ARCH</replaceable>-<!--
        --><replaceable>Version</replaceable>.ami.manifest.xml</screen>

      <para>This completes the S3 specific setup using the bundle created with
        KIWI. The next section explains the use of the disk image file created
        by KIWI to create and EBS backed AMI.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.ec2.using.EBS">
      <title>Using the disk image for and EBS backed AMI</title>
      <para>Inside the destination directory,
        <filename class="directory">/tmp/myec2-result</filename> if you
        followed the commands given above, you will find a file with no
        extension. This file is the filesystem image KIWI created and used to
        create the AMI bundle suitable for use with S3. This filesystem image
        is the one we need to install/dump onto an EBS volume to have an EBS
        backed AMI. In order to create the EBS backed AMI it is necessary
        to work on a running AMI and the local machine that contains the disk
        image file. Further, the running instance must have the
        <command>dd_rescue</command> command available. Using the "regular"
        <command>dd</command> command will result in failure as it does not
        properly handle sparse images. The SUSE Linux Enterprise AMIs available
        in EC2 have the <command>dd_rescue</command> command available. For the
        openSUSE AMIs available in EC2 it is easy to install the
        <command>dd_rescue</command> command by executing zypper as shown
        below.
      
        <screen><command>zypper</command> in dd_rescue</screen></para>

      <para>The first step in creating an EBS backed AMI is to create a
        tarball of the filesystem image file. This is necessary to preserve
        the sparseness properties of the image. Use the <option>-S</option>
        option as shown below. The following commands are executed on your
        build machine.</para>
      
        <screen><command>cd</command> /tmp/myec2-result</screen>
        <screen><command>tar</command> -cSf myImage.tar suse-##.#<!--
          -->-ec2-guest.<replaceable>ARCH</replaceable>-<!--
          --><replaceable>Version</replaceable></screen>
      
      <para>The tarball needs to be uploaded to EC2 and unpacked. This implies
        that the running instance of your chosen AMI needs to have sufficient
        space to store the tarball and the unpacked tarball. Therefore, it is
        recommended to create a storage volume as shown below. The command
        used will return a volume ID that you want to remember and that will
        be referred to as <replaceable>STORE_VOL_ID</replaceable> in this
        example. Execute this command on your local machine.
      
        <screen><command>ec2-create-volume</command> <!--
          -->-s <replaceable>X</replaceable> <!--
          -->-z <replaceable>AV_ZONE</replaceable></screen>
      
        The <replaceable>X</replaceable> is an integer value representing the
        size of the volume to be created in GB (Giga Bytes). The
        <replaceable>AV_ZONE</replaceable> value is one of the Amazon
        availability zones. For all commands presented here the
        <replaceable>AV_ZONE</replaceable> value must be the same. Possible
        values for <replaceable>AV_ZONE</replaceable> are obtained with the
        <command>ec2-describe-availability-zones</command></para>
      
      <para>The next step is to launch an instance of your liking in EC2.
        This instance will be used to create the EBS volume that will
        eventually function as the backing store for your AMI, therefore
        this instance must have the <command>dd_rescue</command> as
        described earlier. Launching the instance is accomplished with the
        <command>ec2-run-instances</command> command executed on your local
         machine.
      
        <screen><command>ec2-run-instances</command> <!--
          -->-k gsgkey <!--
          -->-n 1 <!--
          -->-g <replaceable>SECURITY_GROUP_NAME</replaceable> <!--
          -->-t <replaceable>INSTANCE_TYPE</replaceable> <!--
          -->-z <replaceable>AV_ZONE</replaceable> ami-.....</screen>
      
        The <replaceable>SECURITY_GROUP_NAME</replaceable> is optional, but
        it is best to have a group setup that allows ssh access by default
        to avoid having to open the port all the time as outlined earlier.
        The <replaceable>INSTANCE_TYPE</replaceable> specified with the 
        <option>-t</option> depends on the architecture of your image, for
        example a 64 bit AMI cannot run in a small (m1.small) instance
        type. The <command>ec2-run-instances</command> command returns the
        instance ID, and you want to remember this ID. This ID will be
        referred to as <replaceable>INST_ID</replaceable> in this example.
      </para>
      
      <para>Wait until the instance is running, check the status with the
        <command>ec2-describe-instances</command> command. Once the instance is
        indicated as <emphasis>running</emphasis> attach the previously created
        volume to your instance, by executing the
        <command>ec2-attach-volume</command> command on your local machine.
      
        <screen><command>ec2-attach-volume</command> <!--
          --><replaceable>STORE_VOL_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-i <replaceable>INST_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-d /dev/sdf</screen>
      
        The chosen device specified with the <option>-d</option> is arbitrary,
        however, you do obviously not want to pick a device node that is
        already in use.</para>

      <para>In a different shell login to the running instance as shown in
        the <xref  linkend="sec.ec2.using.general" xrefstyle="select:title"/>
        section.</para>

      <para>Check that the storage volume is attached using the
        <command>ec2-describe-volumes</command> command on your local machine.
        Once the volume is attached the status will be shown as
        <emphasis>in use</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>With the EBS storage volume attached to your instance create a
        filesystem on the volume. There is no need to partition the volume.
        In the EC2 instance that you previously logged into execute the
        <command>mkfs</command> command.
      
        <screen><command>mkfs</command> -t ext3 /dev/sdf</screen>
      
        Once the filesystem creation is complete mount the volume.
      
        <screen><command>mount</command> dev/sdf /mnt</screen></para>

      <para>With the storage volume attched, formated and mounted you now have
        sufficient space to transfer the image tarball you created earlier.
        From the destination directory on your local machine that contains your
        tarball initiate an ftp session to your EC2 instance.
      </para>
      
        <screen><command>sftp</command> <!--
          -->-i <replaceable>PATH_TO_PRIVATE_KEY</replaceable> <!--
          -->root@<replaceable>PUBLIC_IP_OF_YOUR_INSTANCE</replaceable><!--
          -->
sftp><command>cd</command> /mnt
sftp><command>put</command> myImage.tar
sftp><command>bye</command></screen>

      <para>While the image is transfering you can create a new EC2 volume.
        This new volume will become the backing store for your new AMI and
        be referred to as <replaceable>VOL_ID</replaceable> in this example.
        Use the <command>ec2-create-volume</command> command on your local
        machine as shown previously. This time you want to make sure that
        the specified size matches the size of your filesystem image file.
      
        <screen><command>ec2-create-volume</command> <!--
         -->-s <replaceable>Y</replaceable> <!--
         -->-z <replaceable>AV_ZONE</replaceable></screen>
      
        It is good practice to use the <sgmltag class="element">size</sgmltag>
        element in your <filename>config.xml</filename> file when creating EC2
        images. Using the <sgmltag class="element">size</sgmltag> element
        ensures that you have additional space on your root volume and that
        you can match the volume size exactly to your image size.</para>

      <para>As previously, wait for the volume to be created and check the
        status with the <command>ec2-describe-volumes</command> command. When
        the volume creation process is complete, attach the new volume to your
        running instance by executing the <command>ec2-attach-volume</command>
        command on your local machine.

        <screen><command>ec2-attach-volume</command> <!--
          --><replaceable>VOL_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-i <replaceable>INST_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-d /dev/sdg</screen>

        Wait until the status for the volume changes to
        <emphasis>in use</emphasis> before proceeding.</para>

      <para>By now the upload of your image tarball has probably completed and
        you can unpack the image on your storage volume in your EC2 instance.
        In the shell on your EC2 instance unpack the tarball as shown
        below.</para>

        <screen><command>cd</command> /mnt
<command>tar</command> -xSf <!--
          --><replaceable>myImage.tar</replaceable></screen>

      <para>After the unpack operation completes you can dump the filesystem
        image to your EBS volume that will be your backing store for your AMI,
        this volume if attached to /dev/sdg in this example. In the shell
        on your EC2 instance execute te <command>dd_rescue</command> command
        as shown below.

        <screen><command>dd_rescue</command> -a /mnt/suse-##.#-<!--
          -->ec2-guest.<replaceable>ARCH</replaceable>-<!--
          --><replaceable>Version</replaceable> /dev/sdg</screen>

        The <option>-a</option> option instructs dd_rescue to handle the sparse
        file properly. You have to wait until the dump process is complete
        before proceeding to the next step.</para>

      <para>With the dump process complete you can now unmount the storage
        volume from your EC2 instance by executing the following in the
        shell of your running instance.

        <screen><command>umount</command> /mnt</screen>

        You can also exit the shell in your running EC2 instance as all
        remaining commands are executed on your local machine.</para>

      <para>You must detach the volume that is intended as your AMI backing
        store from your running instance. Detaching and deleting the storage
        volume as well as terminating the running instance are optional.

        <screen><command>ec2-detach-volume</command> <!--
          -->-i <replaceable>INST_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-d /dev/sdg <replaceable>VOL_ID</replaceable>

<command>ec2-detach-volume</command> <!--
          -->-i <replaceable>INST_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-d /dev/sdf <replaceable>STORE_VOL_ID</replaceable></screen>

         Prior to shutting down the instance or deleting the storage volume,
         wait until the detach operation has completed. This is indicated by
         the <emphasis>available</emphasis> status in the output of the
         <command>ec2-describe-volumes</command> command.

         <screen><command>ec2-delete-volume</command> <!--
          --><replaceable>STORE_VOL_ID</replaceable>

<command>ec2-terminate-instances</command> <!--
          --><replaceable>INST_ID</replaceable></screen></para>

      <para>Your next step is to create a snapshot of the EBS volume that
        contains your image. The <command>ec2-create-snapshot</command>
        command returns a snapshot ID that you want to remember and will be
        referred to as <replaceable>SNAP_ID</replaceable> in this example.

        <screen><command>ec2-create-snapshot</command> <!--
          -->-d <replaceable>A_SHORT_DESCRIPTION</replaceable> <!--
          --><replaceable>VOL_ID</replaceable></screen>

        The process of creating the snapshot will take a while and depends on
        the size of your volume. Check the status of the snapshot creation
        process using the <command>ec2-describe-snapshots</command> command.
        When the process is complete the status will change to
        <emphasis>100%</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>Once the snapshot is complete you can register it as an AMI with
        the EC2 infrastructure using the <command>ec2-register</command>
        command.

        <screen><command>ec2-register</command> <!--
          -->-d <replaceable>A_DESCRIPTION</replaceable> <!--
          -->-n <replaceable>A_NAME</replaceable> <!--
          -->-s <replaceable>SNAP_ID</replaceable> <!--
          -->-a <replaceable>ARCH</replaceable> <!--
          -->--kernel <replaceable>BOOT_KERNEL_ID</replaceable></screen>

        The <command>ec2-register</command> command will return the AMI ID
        that you can then use to launch your instance.</para>

      <para>The process of creating an EBS backed AMI is a bit tedious. If
        you create EBS backed AMIs more often it might be well worth your time
        to script this process using the Amazon REST API. The EC2 tools
        provided by Amazon that would by name imply to implement this
        process (<command>ec2-import-instance</command> and
        <command>ec2-upload-disk-image</command>) do not handle Linux based
        disk images at the time of this writing.</para>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
