<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                                                 "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="chap.installation">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>KIWI</primary>
        <secondary>Installation</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <sect1 id="sec.installation.rpminstall">
        <title>Installing using Packages</title>
        <para>Once you have added the appropriate repositories (more on
            this below) to your system you can search for the kiwi packages through
            the YaST interface or using <command>zypper</command> as shown
            below.</para>
            
        <screen><command>zypper</command> se kiwi</screen>

        <para>The list of packages returned by zypper contains the main package,
            simply named <filename>kiwi-</filename>, the
            <filename>-doc</filename> package containing the documentation files,
            and  the <filename>-desc-</filename> packages containing the boot
            descriptions for the various image types. Installing this set of
            packages is sufficient to build your images.</para>

        <para>Adding repositories to your system can be accomplished using the
            YaST interface or the <command>zypper ar</command> command.</para>
            
        <sect2 id="sec.installation.distropckgs">
            <title>Distribution Provided Packages</title>
            <para>The simplest and most straight forward way to install KIWI is
                to use the packages that are part of the SUSE distribution you are
                running. In openSUSE the kiwi packages are part of the "standard"
                distribution and in SUSE Linux Enterprise kiwi packages are available
                in the SDK channel.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="sec.installation.studioversion">
            <title>Packages used by SUSE Studio</title>
            <para>If you use SUSE Studio to set up your configuration and then export
                it to build locally on your machine you want to make sure to use the
                same version of KIWI that SUSE Studio uses to build images. This
                version of KIWI which most often differs from the version released
                with a given distribution is available from the openSUSE Build
                Service. The repository you want to add to your system is
                <filename>http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/home:/ctso/<!--
                --><replaceable>DISTRO</replaceable></filename>.</para>
    
            <para>Once you have the repository added to your system you can search
                for the kiwi packages and install them as described above.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="sec.installation.develreleases">
            <title>Packages for Development Releases</title>
            <para>KIWI is under active development and changes almost on a daily
                basis. The development code is generally released once a week on
                Friday. Sometimes the development releases contain new bugs that break
                existing builds. Therefore, this is not necessarily the best release
                stream to track if you are looking for critical on time builds of
                already configured appliances. However, tracking this stream provides
                a great opportunity for you to help in detecting such bugs and by
                reporting them on the mailing list you can help the developers. Any
                regression fixes are generally released as soon as they are completed.
                Thus, there is no need to wait until the next scheduled release on a
                Friday. If you add the <filename>http://download.opensuse.org/<!--
                    -->repositories/Virtualization:/Appliances/<!--
                    --><replaceable>DISTRO</replaceable></filename> repository to
             your system you can track the development release.</para>
    
            <para>Once you have the repository added to your system you can search
                for the kiwi packages and install them as described above.</para>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec.installation.fromsource">
        <title>Installing from Source</title>
        <para>KIWI is developed and maintained in a git repository on GitHub.
            You can clone the source code using the following command.</para>

        <screen><command>git</command> clone <!--
             -->https://github.com/openSUSE/kiwi.git</screen>

        <para>Before installing from source you want to verify that all the
            dependencies are satisfied. The best way to accomplish this is to
            install all packages listed as <emphasis>BuildRequires</emphasis>
            in the <filename>.spec</filename> file found in the
            <filename>rpm</filename> directory. Once all dependent packages are
            installed change your working directory to the
            <filename>kiwi</filename> directory and build and install from
            source.</para>

        <screen><command>make</command>
<command>make</command> install</screen>

        <para>The KIWI self tests are executed using:</para>

        <screen><command>make</command> test</screen>

        <para>If you want to refresh your source with the latest checked in code
            you can simply pull the latest sources from the GitHub repository
            using the command shown below.</para>

        <screen><command>git</command> pull</screen>

    </sect1>
</chapter>
